<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 19. of Iuli 1579 setting forth the excellencye of Gods heauenlye worde: The exceeding mercye of Christ our Sauior: the state of this world: A profe of the true Church: A detection of the false Church: or rather malignant rable: A confutation of sundry hæresies: and other thinges necessary to the vnskilfull to be knowen. By Iohn Dyos. Seene and allowed.</title>
            <author>Dyos, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847243</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12269</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21064)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12269)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 218:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 19. of Iuli 1579 setting forth the excellencye of Gods heauenlye worde: The exceeding mercye of Christ our Sauior: the state of this world: A profe of the true Church: A detection of the false Church: or rather malignant rable: A confutation of sundry hæresies: and other thinges necessary to the vnskilfull to be knowen. By Iohn Dyos. Seene and allowed.</title>
                  <author>Dyos, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 79 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Daye dwelling ouer Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div rend="roman" type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:1"/>
            <p> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermon preached a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Paules Croſſe the 19. of Iuli 1579: ſetting forth the excellencye of Gods heauenlye worde: The exceeding mercye of Chriſt our Sauiour: The ſtate of this world: A profe of the true Church: A detection of the falſe Church: or rather malignant rable: A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of ſundry haereſies: and other thinges neceſſary to the vnſkilfull to be knowen.</p>
            <p>By Iohn Dyos.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Seene and allowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Iohn Daye dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ouer Alderſgate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Anno.</hi> 1579.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Cum Priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:2"/>
            <head>To the right honourable and reuerend Father John by Gods gratious prouidence Byſhop of London, I. D. wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth euerlaſting felicitye.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT (right learned &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Prelate) the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip of the whole world: the great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and beawtye of the celeſtiall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes: the inuiolable order which they keepe in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall &amp; moſt ſwift mouing: the ineſtimable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites which they yeeld to the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or partes by their ſeaſonable inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunges: the ſtraunge and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme terrible effectes that proceede of their ſecret influences and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: the continuall intercourſes of the dayes and nightes: the orderly ſucceeding of the tymes, as winter,
<pb facs="tcp:12269:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:4"/> Springtyme, Sommer, and Harueſt: the generation of Cloudes, Froſts, dewes, windes, thunder, lightning, and ſuch other impreſſions and alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the ayre: the ſituation of the huge earth in the middes of the world without any proppe or ſtay to hold it vp: the highnes of the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes: the fertilitye of the valleyes: the largenes of the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des: the beawtye and vertue of plantes, trees, herbes, and flowers wherewith the earth is ſo excellently adorned: the vnmeaſurable widenes of the maine ſeas, ſome inuironing the compaſſe of the whole earth, and ſome ſhooting forth into the maine land, to the incomparable commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditye of all countryes: the marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous comming &amp; going of the tides: the dreadfulnes of the waues rayzed by tempeſtuous windes: the great plentye of all kinde of fiſhes and mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in them the amiablenes of the
<pb facs="tcp:12269:4"/> freſhe waters, ſome flowing with reſtleſſe ſtreame into the great Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſea, ſome ſincking into the earth from whence they ſpring, ſome ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in vnmoueable Lakes, and all of them fraught with fiſhes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liuing creatures neceſſarye to the vſe of man: the propagation, multiplication, and preſeruation of all liuing thinges in their ſeuerall kindes; and finally the moſt wiſe and ſkilfull making of man, the Lord of all earthly thinges, who is rightly called μικρόκοσμος, that is to ſay, a litle world whoſe head is euen as it were a litle globe of the world, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth all worldly thinges: doe plainly declare &amp; ſhew that there is a God, a wiſe deuiſer, a mighty wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and fatherly preſeruer &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayner of all thinges, to whome we ought of right to be ſubiect, in ſuch ſort as all our doinges may be agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his will: yet notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:12269:5"/> ſinne the mother of all calamityes hath by the fall of our firſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſo venemouſly infected vs all their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable poſteritye and progenye, and ſo blinded vs: that what God is, and what his will is concerning true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, righteouſnes, and eternall lyfe, wee of our ſelues are vtterly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. Therefore hath he merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully geuen vs his heauenly worde, a rule whereby wee may learne to acknowledge, celebrate, inuocate, and worſhip him according to the ſaying of the kingly Prophet: Thy <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> worde is a lanterne vnto my feete. Of the vertue of this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly word, according to the abilitye which God hath gratiouſly geuen me, I hauing not long ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce publiquely ſpoken, &amp; being earneſtly requeſted of certayne vertuouſly diſpoſed, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate my labours to them &amp; others: haue thought it meete to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie their reaſonable requeſt: which
<pb facs="tcp:12269:5"/> labour I conſecrate to your good Lordſhip, and offer the ſame to your learned iudgement, as a ſcholler to his Maiſter as a ſouldiar to his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne. Wherein my endeuour is to ſeeke the glory of God: to encourage the faythfull: and to bring into the kinges high way of their ſaluation, ſuch as goe aſtray, and daungerouſly wander in the mariſhes of idolatrye and ſuperſtition. Yet I proteſt to your Lordſhip, that conſidering the infelicitye and malignity of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tyme, and the vanitye of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I was almoſt diſcouraged to ſpeake or to write. And if I could doe it without offence to God, I would enioyne mee ſelfe, (not with Pythagoras ſchollars, to fiue yeares ſilence, but) to ſeuen yeares ſilence. <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. Tim. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Theſe be the vnhappy dayes that the Apoſtle ſawe ſo long before, wherein men can not abide ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doctrine. The Prophet Eſai ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:12269:6"/> there were ſchollars in his time that would ſay to their teachers: <hi>Loquimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 30. 10.</note> 
               <hi>nobis placentia:</hi> Speake to vs ſuch thinges as may lyke vs. And truely there are now a dayes I feare me too many ſuch ſcholars: too many it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching eares: too many newfangled perſons, and to many wranglers. But I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted whan I conſider that the veritye ouercommeth fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhod, and that the thinges which are of God, doe daunt whatſoeuer is obiected of men, and of Sathan himſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what hurteth the enemye, yf God protect? what preuaileth enuy, yf the higheſt preſerue? They may mutter and murmure, brawle, and cauill: but they cannot hurt. Truth will get the vpper ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: Chriſt will haue the field. I would to God euery man would ſeeke the truth in the worde of God. S. Auguſt. ſayth: <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onfeſ. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Vbi inueni veritatem: ibi inueni Deum meum ipſam veritatem:</hi> Where I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:12269:6"/> the truth: there I found my God, who is the truth it ſelfe. I would to God men would embrace the truth and now at length ſtick no longer in their mire, but ceaſe to defend the denne of Antichriſt, the houſe of their ſpirituall whoredome, &amp; ſhops of falſhode, fraughted with ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, dreames, pride, vaineglory, and all other abhominable abuſes. It is great pitie that learning ſhould be ſo ill beſtowed. For how much might they be able to doe to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the truth, which ſhew ſo great cunning and ſkill in defence of falſhod? Eraſmus a man of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and exquiſite learning, writte much of the prayſe of follie: what could he haue written in the prayſe of wit? Cornelius Agrippa writte much of the vanitye of ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: what could he haue written in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of ſciences? how could he haue prayſed helth, that prayſed
<pb facs="tcp:12269:7"/> the feuer quartane? how could he haue prayſed bewtifull heare, that prayſed deformed baldnes? how many aduenture witte in deſperate cauſes? It is a deſperate cauſe that can not be ſmoothed with words of eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. No follie ſo vaine, but by ſome ſhift it may be maintayned. By meanes wherof, the blinde drinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth many a flye, and the ſimple eye is ſone beguiled. Yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding their Tranſubſtantiation, their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorye, their Merites, their Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saintes, their Supremacy, and ſuch other Romiſh platyre can not be iuſtly defended by ſcripture or Doctours. Therfore it were good for thoſe kinde of teachers to ceaſe to abuſe the ſimplicitye of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to profeſſe the trueth. S. Ambroſe ſayth: <hi>Nullus pudor eſt ad</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Epiſt. ad Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſium. Tom. 1.</note> 
               <hi>melior a tranſire:</hi> It is no ſhame to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue to the better. Auguſtine was an infant in Chriſtes religion the
<pb facs="tcp:12269:7"/> three and thirtye yeare of his age. S. <note place="margin">in Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donio.</note> Paule began ill: and yet he ended well. Of a cruell perſecutour, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a mighty defender of Chriſtes religion: Of a ſcatterer he became a gatherer: Of a wolfe, a lambe: Of an Antichriſtian enemy, a Chriſtian ſouldiar: Of a learnd lawier at Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, a learner of the Goſpell at Damaſcus: and of a Saul, a Paul.</p>
            <p>God of his mercy graunt that all they which haue traced the path of Antichriſt, may renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe dreames, and fonde aſſertions, and (after the example of S. Paule) profeſſe Chriſt: deteſt Antichriſt: &amp; goe forward in all godlynes, euen vnto their liues end. Dauid may fall, and Saule may riſe. Wee ought to hope the beſt of all men, to iudge the beſt, and to thinke the beſt: For charity thinketh no euill. S. Auguſt. ſayth wel: <hi>Bononorum deſyderu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt vt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> 
               <hi>qui mali ſunt corrigantur: ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:8"/> 
               <hi>eſt vt qui boni ſunt conſumantur:</hi> Good men would faine haue ill men amended: and ill men would faine haue good men conſumed. There are too many ſuch in this doting age of the world, which hate all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> extremely that pleaſe not their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: yet they make great ſhew of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes. But if their viſardes were pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of, (Good Lord,) what a maſſe of malice ſhould a man ſee? what enuy, what falſhode, what ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, &amp; rancour ſhould a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold? Turkes and Iewes are better to be lyked, than ſuch hipocriticall Chriſtians. Charitye ouer commeth all thinges: without charity nothing preuaileth: and whereſoeuer chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye is, ſhee draweth all thinges vnto her: and ſhee is the bewtye of the ſoule. I ſurceaſe humbly and harte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeeching Chriſt the Prince of Paſtours to perſerue your honour by the vertue of his holy Spirite many
<pb facs="tcp:12269:8"/> yeares, to the aduauncement of his glory: to the repayring of the ruines of Sion: To the vtter ruin of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and finally after your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrination vpon earth, to geue you the laborers peny of euerlaſting bleſſednes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At London <date>the 2. day of September.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips alwayes moſt humble at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Iohn Dyos.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:9"/>
               <l>COntio Dios celebrata crebris</l>
               <l>Vocibus, flexit populum potentem,</l>
               <l>At<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> plebeios animos rigauit</l>
               <l>Nectare ſuaui.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pauit aeternis epulis Iehouae</l>
               <l>Indigas mentes: ſitibunda prata:</l>
               <l>Rore diuino, fluuio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſparſit</l>
               <l>Corda ſalubri.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fregit &amp; vires Latij Tyranni,</l>
               <l>Praeſcidit criſtas: triplicem coronam</l>
               <l>Contudit: fido Salios ſalaces</l>
               <l>Arguit ore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Inuidi Momi maleſuada lingua</l>
               <l>Putreat: corui lanient doloſos</l>
               <l>Zoilos: Laruae valeant: faceſſat</l>
               <l>Dira Megaera.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>ק. ב</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <lg>
               <head>Papa loquitur.</head>
               <l>NOs pedibus noſtris dominos ſupponimus orbis:</l>
               <l>Nos plantis premimus, Caeſareum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> genus.</l>
               <l>Si placeat, Genios volumus detrudere coelo:</l>
               <l>Noſtra manus Manes ex Acheronte vocat.</l>
               <l>Poſse ſacerdotes Paniſcum condere Chriſtum,</l>
               <l>Dicimus: Ergo Dei gloria danda mihi.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:9"/>
               <l> Nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> creatorem mundi facit ille: quis ipſe?</l>
               <l>Nonne Deus ſummus? ſolus vtrun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> creo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Maior caelitibus ſacrifex, genijs<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſupremis:</l>
               <l>Sacrificis praeſto: dicite, quantus ego?</l>
               <l>Sacrificus praeſtat Mariae: ſemel illa gerebat</l>
               <l>Chriſtum: ſed ſacrifex ſaepius ore vorat.</l>
               <l>Saepius ore vorat, carnem cum ſaenguine crudo,</l>
               <l>Oſſa vorat, pectus, brachia, crura pedes.</l>
               <l>Eſt noſtrum genus, eximijs ſpectabile factis,</l>
               <l>Gregorius Magnus carminae mirae canit:</l>
               <l>Chriſto pulſanti patuit vix ianua Ditis:</l>
               <l>Sed mihi pulſanti mox paetuere fores.</l>
               <l>Nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ego Trae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>um tetri de faucib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Orci</l>
               <l>Extr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xi, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>trem, Dite fremente meam.</l>
               <l>Semper bonos, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> meum, laudeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> manebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</l>
               <l>Quae Chriſtus c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndis, condere iure queo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Chriſtus reſpondet.</head>
               <l>TV lupus, et vulpes: Tu ſummum de decus orbis:</l>
               <l>Tu ruis in baerathrum: te manet atra dies.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:10"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Sermon Preached at Paules Croſſe, the xix. day of Iuly. An.</hi> 1579.</head>
            <byline>By Iohn Dyos.</byline>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luc. 5.</bibl>
               <q rend="roman">IT came to paſſe, that (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people preaſſed vpon him, to heare the word of God) he ſtode by the lake of Genezareth, and ſawe two ſhyppes ſtand by the lakes ſide, but the fiſherme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were gone out of them, and were wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing their nettes. And he entred into one of the ſhippes (whiche pertained to Simon) and prayd him that hee would thruſt out a litle from the land. And hee ſat down, and taught the people out of the ſhippe. When he had left ſpeakyng, hee ſayd vnto Simon: launche out into the deepe, and let ſlippe your nettes to make a draught. And Simon aunſwered and ſayd vnto hym: Maiſter, we haue laboured all night, &amp; haue taken nothing. Neuertheleſſe, at
<pb facs="tcp:12269:11"/> thy commaundement I will loſe forth the nette. And when they had ſo done, they incloſed a great multitude of fiſhes. But their net brake, and they beckned to their felowes (which were in the other ſhippe) that they ſhould come and helpe them. And they came and filled both ſhippes, that they ſonke agayne. When Simon Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaw this, he fell down at Ieſus knees, ſaying: Lord go from me, for I am a ſinnefull man. For he was aſtonyed, and all that were with hym, at the draught of the fiſhes which they had taken, and ſo was alſo Iames and Iohn the ſonnes of Zebede, whiche were parteners with Simon. And Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſayd vnto Symon: Feare not, from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth thou ſhalt catch men. And they brought the ſhippes to land, and forſoke all, and followed him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12269:11"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is written in the 5. <hi>of Luke:</hi> and read in the Churche this day: <hi rend="roman">It came to paſſe, that when the people preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon him to heare the worde of God, he was ſtandyng by the lake of Genezareth. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ende of the former chapter (Chriſtian audience) Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour being ill intreated in Nazareth (no Prophet is accepted in his owne countrey) came downe to Caphernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Citie of Galilee, &amp; there taught the people on the Sabboth dayes, caſt out deuils, and cured Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wiues mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſicke of a great feuer, and when the ſunne was downe, healed what ſoeuer ſicke were brought to hym, laying his handes on euery of them. Deuils alſo came out of many, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſaying: Thou art that Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God. &amp;c. There they preaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and here they preaſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of all: Séeke ye firſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 33.</note> the kyngdome of God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and all theſe thynges ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:12269:12"/> miniſtred vnto you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The text principally compriſeth theſe thrée places: an Example, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to heare the Goſpell feruently, and the cauſes therof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſhip wherein Chriſt was, is an image of the Church of Chriſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, the requeſt of Chriſt and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience of Peter.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The ſucceſſe of all. </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It came to paſſe when the people preaſſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to heare the word of God.</hi> Sinfull men of euery condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preaſſed vppon him to heare his heauenly doctrine. We neuer read of any ſuch preaſſing of Scribes &amp; Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeis to Chriſt: I thanke thee O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 25.</note> Lord of heauen &amp; earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe thynges from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt ſhewed them vnto babes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The people preaſſed vpon him to heare the word of God.</hi> Luc. ſayth not, people came to him, &amp;c. But the people preaſſed vppon him. Theſe wordes are very emphaticall, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, notifieng the feruent ſtudy of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12269:12"/> thoſe people to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God. For this cauſe: they followed him from Galilee, from Decapolis, from Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from Iudea, from beyond Iordan. They followed him aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</note> to the mountaine, they folowed him deſcending from the mountaine: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.</note> they folowed him to the ſea ſide, they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc.</hi> 3.</note> folowed on foote to the wilderneſſe. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.</note> Whether dyd they not follow him? The paynefull clyming of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15,</note> did nothyng diſcourage them, the high craggye rockes did nothyng terrifie them, the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtuous waues of the ſea did nothyng diſmay them. Great multitudes came vnto hym: lame, blynd, dombe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of multitudes folowyng, read Mar. 3. &amp;. 8. Luk. 6. Ioh. 6. Mat. 15. Certaine women folowed him with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note> multitude of other folkes, and they that caryed the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſick of the Palſey, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 5.</note> becauſe of the preaſſe, went vp on the top of the houſe, and let him downe through the roofe, You alſo heare how to day they preaſſed vpon him. They departed not from him ſodeinly, but
<pb facs="tcp:12269:13"/> continued ſometyme iij. whole dayes with him: and not a few: ſometyme iiij. thouſand, ſome tyme v. thouſand at a tyme, beſide women &amp; children. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.</note> You ſée how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people in thoſe dayes, feruently preſſed vpon Chriſt, payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully folowed him, louingly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued with him. They folowed him to the wildernes, to heare the ſweetenes of his word: wee Citizens hauyng the ſame within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walles of Cities, loue it not, but ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ragingly contemne it. They taryed with him whole dayes: we thincke long to tary with him few houres: and thinke not long to wayte vpon vanitie many houres: Euery thyng encreaſeth ſauyng godlyneſſe. Houſes now are more large, &amp; ſmoke leſſe, more eatyng, more drinkyng, more ſléepyng, more ſpendyng, more coſt for apparel: more vanitie in talk; &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more vitious: but at Sermons in any caſe we cannot tary longer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an houre: It is tedious to many, to tary ſo long. They preaſſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: we leiſurely, and ſlowly ſcarce come to him. To the worlde, as quicke as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12269:13"/> bées: to the word, as flow as ſnayles. They heard him atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiuely: we heare him negligently, without courage, as we were halfe aſléepe, and our mynd a pilgrimage, coldly, coldly. Such is the behauiour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of this tyme: ſuch is the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of the word: ſuch is the folly of men: ſuch is the loue of earthly thynges, &amp; hate of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things. And therfore looke ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for plague and puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They preaſſed vpon him:</hi> Not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hickſcorner: not vpon Iack Iuglar: not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tomtumbler: not vpon cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptours &amp; deſtroyers, as vayne men of our tyme: but vpon him, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon Ieſus Chriſt, the Phiſicion of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.</note> the light of the world, the expreſſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.</note> Image of the inuiſible God, the firſt borne of all creatures, the wiſedome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 1.</note> &amp; power of God: the way, the truth, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> and lyfe: the Prince of Paſtours, the great ſhepheard of our ſoules, the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.</note> founder and finiſher of our fayth, the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> Euangelicall henne, the true Vyne, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ebru.</hi> 12.</note> the bread of lyfe, the rocke and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the liuyng waters, the <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:14"/> the bleſſed ſéede, the reconciler <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. <hi>Marc.</hi> 12. <hi>Luc.</hi> 20. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 9. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 62. <hi>Luc.</hi> 4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. <hi>Malach.</hi> 4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. <hi>Num.</hi> 24. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. <hi>Ebru.</hi> 7. 8. 9. <hi>Oſe.</hi> 13. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Zach.</hi> 13. <hi>Ebru.</hi> 1.</note> of God and man, the cornerſtone of the buildyng, the foundation of the ſame, the kyng of glory, the prince of peace, the high Prieſt, the annoynted of God, the lambe of God that taketh away the ſinnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, the hope and rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of Iſraell, <hi>Iacobs lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> whereby we clyme to the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent father, the ſonne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the true light, the ſtarre of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, the mercyfull Samaritane, the price of our redemption, our ſacrifice for ſinne, our ſatiſfaction, our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, our guide, our way to God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conquerour of Death, Hell, Sinne, &amp; Sathan, the giuer of lyfe, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of grace &amp; veritie. They preaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon him whoſe nobilitie, riches, wiſedome, bewtie, ſtrength, puritie, honour and goodnes can neuer be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently commended: without him, our light is full of darkeneſſe: Our ſtrength full of weakenes, our truth full of falſehode, our perfection full of imperfection. He is good, we are euil: yea our nature is euill. Saint Auſten <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 3.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12269:14"/> ſaith, <hi>Nemo erit bonus qui non erat ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. de Ciuit. Dei Lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> None ſhalbe good, which hath not bene euill. He onely is happy, we are miſerable wretches. He is omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; eternall, we are weake, yea weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it ſelfe, duſt and corruption.</p>
            <p>By his righteouſnes, we be made righteous: by his holyneſſe, we be made holy: by his glory we are glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. It is honeſt and comely, that the wayfaryng man ſhoulde folow his guide: The creature, his creator: the ſaued, his Sauiour: The ſubiectes their king: the ſheepe their ſhepheard: the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, their maiſter: the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, their teacher: the members their head: the children their parentes: the ſouldiours their captaine: the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts their Phiſicion.</p>
            <p>He is our guide, we are the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men: he is our creator, we his creatures: he our Sauiour, we the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: he is our kyng, we his ſubiectes: he our ſhepheard, we his ſhéepe: he our maſter, we his vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes: he our heauenly ſcholemai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, we his negligent ſcholers: he our
<pb facs="tcp:12269:15"/> head, we his members: he our father, we his children: he our captaine, we his ſouldiours: hee the omnipotent Phiſicion, we the faint and féeble pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientes. Therfore it is good to folow him, to preaſſe vpon him, &amp; with the diſſeaſed woman to touch him. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider the cauſe why they preaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon him. The finall cauſe why they preaſſed vpon him, was to heare the word of God: note their feruent deſire to heare the word of God. The worde of God: not the traditions of men, not vanities, as vayne men of our dayes preaſſe to heare vanities, yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the Sabboth day, which is intolerable. The Sabboth day ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecrate to the ſeruice of God. The true ſanctifieng and halowyng of this day, conſiſteth in the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippyng of God. Many other folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; preaſſed on him for other cauſes.</p>
            <p>The hypocriticall Phariſeis fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 16. 4.</note> and preaſſed, to deride him.</p>
            <p>Some folowed &amp; preaſſed, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie. Such were the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Athens, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 21.</note> which gaue them ſelues to nothyng
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12269:15"/> els, but either to tell, or to heare ſome newes. We haue multitudes of men of Athens now a dayes.</p>
            <p>Some preaſſed to ſée his miracles: <hi>Vidimus mirabilia hodie:</hi> we haue ſene ſtraunge thynges to day. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 5. 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Some to get bodily health. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Some folow <hi>Chriſtum Fortunatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> wealthy &amp; rich Chriſt, for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. <hi>Luc.</hi> 9.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maybe enriched, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that offered his ſeruice to Chriſt, ſaying, maiſter I wil folow thee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> goeſt: And Ieſus au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red &amp; ſaid to him: Fores haue holes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byrdes of the ayre haue neſts: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath not where to reſt his head. The Foxe hath his hole in hipo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crites: the byrdes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuils, haue their neſtes in hypocrites: no place for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hipocrites.</p>
            <p>Some folow and preaſſe for their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.</note> belly ſake: as thoſe which ſayd, <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi</hi> when cameſt thou hither? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Some to enta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle him in his talke. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Luc.</hi> 20. <hi>Marc.</hi> 12. <hi>Origen: in Mat. cap.</hi> 22</note> The auncient father Origen calleth all them brethren of the Phariſeis, which ſéeke to entrap men. And <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> a learned man ſayth: <hi>Diabolicum</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:16"/> 
               <hi>est quaerere quod carpas, quod damnes:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aretius in Pſal.</hi> 1.</note> It is deuiliſhe to ſéeke to taunt, to carpe, to condemne.</p>
            <p>Some folowed him to ſée: as vaine curious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do now a dayes, which come to Sermons to ſee, and not to learne: <hi>Domine volumus a te ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 38.</note> Maiſter we would ſée a ſigne of thee: but he aunſwered and ſayd vnto them: this euill and adulterous gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſéeketh a ſigne: but there ſhall no ſigne be geuen to it, ſaue the ſigne of the Prophet Ionas.</p>
            <p>Some preaſſe to heare inuectiues.</p>
            <p>Some to be more ready to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: and a few (alas to few) for the loue of Gods holy worde, as this company. And yet not vnlike but that ſome of them afterward cried: <hi>Tolle eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fige</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19. 15.</note> 
               <hi>eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> away with him, crucifie him. Such is the inconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, of the vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant multitude. To this tendeth the parable of the ſéede: ſome fell by the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>Marc.</hi> 4. <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note> hygh wayes ſide, ſome vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtony pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſome among thornes, &amp; ſome fell into good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; brought forth frute, ſome an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred fold, ſome ſixtie, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12269:16"/> ſome thyrtie folde. Thus much for that point.</p>
            <p>By the word of God, I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d here the word of the Goſpell, that is, that Ieſus is the true Meſſias, the ſonne of the woman of whom it is ſayd, <hi>Conteret caput Serpentis:</hi> he ſhall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> breake the Serpentes head, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly vanquiſh the power and puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> of Sathan. That ſonne of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, in whom all the nations of the earth ſhalbe bleſſed. The ſonne of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> Dauid, which in the houſe of Iacob ſhall raigne for euer. That ſonne to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> whom it is ſayd: aſke of me &amp; I will giue thée the Heathen for thine inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.</note> &amp; ſit thou on my right hand till I make thine enemyes thy foote ſtole. To be ſhort, that ladder of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.</note> which reacheth to heauen.</p>
            <p>Chriſt taught ſometyme the law, ſometyme the Goſpell. Albeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Chriſt in the v. vj. &amp; vij. Math. is a true interpretation of the law: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the law is not the thyng, for preachyng whereof Chriſt was ſent in to this world. For (as we
<pb facs="tcp:12269:17"/> read in Eſay. 61. 1. verſ.) The ſpirit of the Lord is vpon me, for the Lord hath annoynted me, and ſent me to preach good tidynges vnto the poore. Chriſt came not as a law maker, or a law teacher, as Moyſes came before. Hereunto is added, that the word of the law doth ſlea or kill, as S. Paule <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6.</note> teacheth: but the word of Chriſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life, as he teſtifieth him ſelfe: ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly veryly I ſay vnto you, if a man <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 51.</note> kéepe my ſaying, hee ſhall neuer ſée death.</p>
            <p>The law is a knowledge knowen <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> by nature, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth: The Goſpel is not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nature, but publiſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſecret determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Godhead, by our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>Lex per Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>data est: gratia, &amp; veritas per Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facta eſt:</hi> The law was ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen by Moyſes, but grace and truth came by Ieſus Chriſt. And our Saui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our ſaith to his diſciples: To you it is geuen to know the ſecretes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.</note> of God. &amp;c. And alſo to Peter he ſayth, fleſh &amp; bloud hath not opened
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12269:17"/> that vnto thée, but my father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Read. 1. Cor. 2. &amp; 1. Cor. 4. 2 Cor. 5. Colloſ. 4. 1. Tim. 3. Rom. 16.</p>
            <p>The law ſheweth ſinne: The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ſheweth Chriſt the Sauiour of the world, teachyng that ſinnes are forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleue in him, &amp; that they are reconciled to God. Theſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</note> thynges do the wiſemen, Prophetes, &amp; Scribes ſpecially teach, which are ſent from the ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>The law requireth onely obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth the guilty: The Goſpell giueth remiſſion of ſinnes, freely in the name of Chriſt to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent: relieueth and comforteth the troubled conſciences, with his ſweete promiſes.</p>
            <p>The promiſes of the law are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> ye ſhal kéepe my ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and my iudgementes: which if a man do, he ſhall liue in them: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell are certaine and free: Come to the waters all ye that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 55.</note> be thirſty, and ye that haue no money come buy wyne and milke, without any money or moneys worthe. All <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:18"/> haue ſinned and haue néede of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, but are iuſtified fréely by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 16.</note> his grace, through the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption that is in Chriſt Ieſus. Therfore by fayth is the inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it might be by grace.</p>
            <p>The law propoſeth preceptes: the Goſpell hath promiſes. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The law is a rule of good workes: the Goſpell is a doctrine of the perſon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> and benefites of the Meſſias.</p>
            <p>The law denounceth the wrath of God, eternall malediction; death and damnation to all men for ſinne: <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. <hi>vlt. verſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>omnis qui no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerit in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus his. &amp;c:</hi> Curſed be he that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth not in all the woordes of this law, to do them, &amp; all the people ſhall ſay Amen: The Goſpell offereth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes to all men: To giue <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> knowledge of ſaluation to his people for the remiſſion of their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>The law iuſtifieth none, ſaueth none, deliuereth none from ſinne, but accuſeth, bewrayeth ſinne, &amp; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all: the Goſpell of Chriſt is the power of God to ſaluation, to all that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12269:18"/> beleue, offeryng to all remiſſion of ſinnes, rightuouſnes, &amp; eternall life.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort the law is to be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thundered to the wicked, negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and impenitent: the Goſpell is ſweetely to be ſounded, to thoſe that acknowledge their ſinnes and hartily repent for the ſame. The ſwéete pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt teacheth the ſame: Come vnto me all ye that labour ſore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28.</note> and are laden and I will eaſe you. &amp;c. Of this we haue example in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet Nathan: who by a ſimilitude, thundered the law agaynſt kyng <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> repenteth ſaying: I haue ſinned againſt the Lord: Nathan pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the Goſpell: The Lorde hath put away thy ſinne, thou ſhalt not dye.</p>
            <p>The worde of God, or doctrine of Chriſt, is called the worde of God: that is, the doctrine which Chriſt him ſelfe reuealed to men. Whereof the principall point, is frée remiſſion and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, by fayth in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The efficient cauſe of this Goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:12269:19"/> is the whole Godhead: the eternall Father, eternall Sonne, and eternall holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The mouyng cauſe, is the excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng mercy of God, and his paſſyng loue toward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd. So God loued <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 16.</note> the world, that he gaue his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne: that whoſoeuer beleueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng lyfe.</p>
            <p>The firſt inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall cauſe, is the ſonne of God our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. An other inſtrumentall cauſe, are the Prophetes, Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes &amp; other teachers of the doctrine of the Goſpell. Therfore the Apoſtle ſayth, Let men eſtéeme vs as the Miniſters <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> of Chriſt, and diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God. We together are Gods la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 9. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20</note> &amp;c. we are meſſengers for Chriſt, euen as though God did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech you through vs.</p>
            <p>The materiall cauſe, is Chriſt with all his benefites.</p>
            <p>The formall cauſe, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gladſome meſſage of free remiſſion of ſinnes, purchaſed by Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12269:19"/>
            <p> The finall cauſe, is that mankynd beyng deliuered out of the handes of his enemies Death, Sinne, Hell, &amp; Sathan, ſhould ſerue God in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of his lyfe.</p>
            <p>He that is of God, heareth Gods word, he loueth it, beleueth it, &amp; doth it. Theſe thyngs are included in the word <hi>Heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word of God hath ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> ſome receiue it, ſome receiue it not. Note y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parable of the ſeede. The <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.</note> ſéede of the word of God when it was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc.</hi> 4.</note> ſowed, fell ſome by the wayes ſide, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note> ſome vpon ſtones, ſome vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thornes, and ſome in good ground &amp;c. but more ſtrictly and briefly, the word of God hath two ſortes of heares: Elect and Reprobate. The elect ſay with Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>Domine ad quem ibimus? verba vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae aeternae habes:</hi> Maiſter to whom ſhal <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.</note> we goe? thou haſt the wordes of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe. The reprobate ſay: <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo:</hi> This is a hard ſaying, who can heare it? Can this mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie put on immortalitie? Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb facs="tcp:12269:20"/> put on incorruption? Can Chriſt be God and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Can God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a ſonne, as of late y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche deuiliſhlye ſayde? yea worſe then a deuill was he. For the deuils in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former Chapter acknowledged Chriſt, crying and ſaying: Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of God: but this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill denyed Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The word of God is preached in vayne to many, the hony is loſt, that is put into veſſels of gall: the fiſhe is caſt away, that is caſt into dry pooles: and the ſéede periſheth, that is ſowed vpon the ſand. S. Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth: <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyp. contra Demetria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>labor irritus eſt &amp; nullius effectus, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre lumen coeco, ſermonem ſurdo, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiam bruto: Cum nec ſentire bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poſſit, nec coecus lume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admittere, nec ſurdus audire:</hi> Truly it is loſt labor and to no purpoſe: to offer light to a blind ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpeach to a deafe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to a groſſe head, ſeyng that a groſſe head cannot perceiue, a blinde man can not ſee, a deafe man can not heare. The auncient father Origen <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen. in Nume.</hi> 6. <hi>Hom.</hi> 3.</note> ſayth: <hi>Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to melius eſſet nonnullis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12269:20"/> 
               <hi>non audire verbum Dei, quam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire cum malitia, vel audire cum hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſi: melius autem dicimus ad compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem malorum:</hi> How much better were it to ſome, not to heare the word of God at all, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to heare it with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or to heare it with hypocriſie: we ſay better, in reſpect of euils.</p>
            <p>Excellent is this word: therefore ought we to heare it.</p>
            <p>It differreth from ours manifold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: in truth, for God is true, yea truth it ſelfe: man is falſe, yea falſhode it <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.</note> ſelfe: <hi>Omnis homo mandax:</hi> Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.</note> is a lyer.</p>
            <p>It differeth from ours in profit: Lord to whom ſhall we go (ſayth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.</note> thou haſt the wordes of eternall lyfe: our wordes haue no profit, they are wordes of eternall death.</p>
            <p>It differeth in certaintie, for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry truth and certainty it ſelfe ſayth: that the moſt firme Elements of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> &amp; earth ſhall paſſe, but his word ſhall in no wiſe paſſe. The Prophet Eſay ſayth: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbum Domini manet in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 40. 8.</note> 
               <hi>aeternum:</hi> The word of the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth
<pb facs="tcp:12269:21"/> for euer: Mary hath choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the good part, which ſhall not be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. 42.</note> from her: our wordes are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as vnconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as the Weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke. We ſay and vnſay, and vnſay and ſay againe. That which liketh vs to day, miſliketh vs to morow.</p>
            <p>It differeth in power: as ſoone as hee had ſayd to the band of men, and officers of the hyghe Prieſtes, I am <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.</note> he: they went backewarde and fell to the grounde. Note here the power of the word of God: They came ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, they came to take Ieſus: and after they heard his mightfull word, they fell to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Mathew ſayth: <hi>Docebat eos ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quam authoritatem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>vl.. verſ.</hi>
               </note> He taught them as one hauyng power, and not as the Scribes: Our wordes are ſinnefull, corrupt, and vnperfect.</p>
            <p>It differeth in ſpirit: The wordes that I ſpeake vnto you, are ſpirit and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 63.</note> lyfe: But our wordes are prophane and tranſitorie. Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Qui de terra eſt, terrenus eſt &amp; de terra loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> He that is of the earth is earthly,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12269:21"/> and ſpeaketh of the earth.</p>
            <p>It differeth from our woordes in ſwéetnes: The ſeruaunts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis &amp; high Prieſtes, which were ſent to take Chriſt, returned and ſaid thus of the excellencie of his word, <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſic loquutus eſt homo:</hi> Neuer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. 46.</note> ſpake as this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth. Not Demoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes, out of whoſe mouth flowed fluddes of eloquence: not Cicero the Father of eloquence: not eloquent Pericles, of whom it is written, that he did thunder out his wordes. But Chriſtes Argumentes were ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and his woordes ſo ſwéete, that a certaine woman hauyng great admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therof: lifted vp her voyce and ſayd vnto him: happy is the wombe that bare thée, and the pappes which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 11. 27.</note> thou haſt ſucked.</p>
            <p>To be brief, this word differeth in perfection: In his word all things en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 43. 26.</note> Take away this perfect word, what is man? a brute beaſt.</p>
            <p>Take the Sunne out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, what remaineth? Horrible darknes. <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſayth: <hi>Lumen me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactan. de ira Dei cap.</hi> 1.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:22"/> 
               <hi>Deus eſt: remoto Deo coeleſti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina omnia erroribus plena ſunt:</hi> God is the light of mans ſoule: If you ſet a ſide, or put away from you God &amp; his heauenly word: All thynges are ful of errours. Take away this word, what is a man? a captiue of Sathan, a pray of death, a ſlaue of ſinne, a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand of hell: <hi>Ignorantia Scripturaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hierom. in Prologo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiae.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſti ignorantia eſt:</hi> Ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scriptures is ignoraunce of Chriſt. As far as heauen is diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth: ſo farre ought heauenly thynges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be preferred before humane things: yea incomparably ought they alwayes to be preferred.</p>
            <p>It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to the Sunne, whoſe office is, by ſpreadyng of his radiant and bright beames to expell darknes, and to diſpoſe euery thyng to beare frute: Right ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of Gods word is, with his bright &amp; ſhinyng beames of grace to expell the darknes of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies &amp; errours, to take away the cold froſt of iniquitie, and to diſpoſe and frame euery man and woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bring forth the frutes of pietie &amp; godlynes.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12269:22"/>
            <p> It is compared to fier, for that it enflameth vs by loue. The two Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples whiche went to Emans, ſayd (after that Chriſt had interpreted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in all the Scriptures) did not our hartes burne within vs while he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 24. 23.</note> talked with vs by the way, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to vs the Scriptures? and Chriſt ſayth, I am come to ſend fier on the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 12. 49.</note> earth, and what is my deſire, but that it be already kindled?</p>
            <p>It is likened to a glaſſe: in this glaſſe euery man may ſée whence he came, what he is, whether he goeth: his ſin, his baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, his miſerie. S. Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geueth ſwéet cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaile to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain virgin: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tere lectione diuina, vte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hierom: in Epiſto. ad Demetria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> 
               <hi>speculo, vide ſpeculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, foeda corrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, pulchra co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da, &amp; pulchra facie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. Scriptura enim ſpeculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt foeda oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, &amp; corrige dicens:</hi> Vſe to read the holy Scripture, vſe the glaſſe, ſée the glaſſe: That deformitie may be ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, fayreneſſe preſerued, and fayre thynges performed. For the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a glaſſe ſhewyng deformitie, &amp; ſaying amend. Gregory ſayth: <hi>Sacra</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:23"/> 
               <hi>Scriptura tanquam ſpeculum quoddam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gregor. in moral.</note> 
               <hi>mentis:</hi> The holy Scripture is as a certaine glaſſe of the mynde. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. ſayth: <hi>Scriptura ſancta ſit tibi ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 48.</note> 
               <hi>speculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Speculum hoc habet ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorem non me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacem, non adulante<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius perſonam amantem. Formoſus es? Formoſum te ibi vides. Sed cum foedus acceſſeris, &amp; foedum te ibi videris, noli accuſare speculum: ad te redi, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit ſpeculum, tu te noli fallere:</hi> Let the holy Scripture be to thée as a glaſſe. This glaſſe hath no deceitfull or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teryng brightneſſe, it is not in loue with any mans perſon. Art thou bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull? Thou ſéeſt thy ſelfe there bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull. But when thou commeſt defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; ſéeſt thy ſelfe there deformed: accuſe not the glaſſe, aduiſe thée ſelfe. The glaſſe deceiueth thée not, deceiue not thou thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>It is lyke to a cleare fountaine or well. The woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Samaria found <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.</note> Chriſt at the well. Would you finde Chriſt? At the well of his word ſhall you finde him.</p>
            <p>S. Baſill ſayth, the Scripture of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſil. in Pſal.</hi> 1.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12269:23"/> God is like to Apothecaries ſhop full of medecines ſundry ſortes, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man may there choſe a conuenient remedy for his diſſeaſe.</p>
            <p>This is that pillar exhibited to the children of Iſraell: <hi>Factae ſunt tene brae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. 22</note> 
               <hi>horribiles in vniuerſa terra Aegypti, vbicunque habitabant filij Iſrael lux e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat:</hi> There was a thicke darknes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Egypt: but all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell had light where they dwelled. Where the word of God is, there is light: Where the ſame is not, there is darkenes. Without this fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie piller, we can not walke in the light. He that walketh in darkneſſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12. 35.</note> knoweth not whether he goeth. This is that piller which mightely condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. 21</note> our vnderſtandyng, out of the the Egypt of infidelitie. This is that Lucifer the bright mornyng ſtarre, whiche commeth before the ſunne of righteouſneſſe, by whom the light of grace doth riſe, whom foloweth the day of glory.</p>
            <p>This is that ſtarre of the ſea, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crying port and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey to the ſaylers
<pb facs="tcp:12269:24"/> on the ſea of this world. This is that ſtarre, which led the wiſe and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a far countrey to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This is that moſt heauenly iewell <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 45.</note> &amp; treaſure, the precious ſtone whiche the Chriſtian Marchantman ſought with great dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and care<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; when he had found it, ſold all that he had to buy the ſame. He whiche preferreth the word of God before all tranſitorie thynges: Which for ſaketh him ſelfe, taketh vp his Croſſe, and foloweth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 24.</note> Chriſt, is truly ſayd to ſell all that he hath, and to buy the ſame.</p>
            <p>This is a moſt pleaſaunt garden. In this garden you may gather many ſwéete flowers: the plantain of ſayth, the roſes of patience, the lillies of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, the oliues of mercy, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of moſt excellent vertue. In this garden are planted many goodly and fayre trées, bringyng forth moſt ſwéet and deliteſome frute: The Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of contemplation, the Cypruſſes of noble fame, the Okes of conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, the Laurels or Bay trées of vertue, and many other ſuch like.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12269:24"/>
            <p> It is called a candle or light. The kingly Prophet ſayth: thy word is a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.</note> candle vnto my féete, and a light vnto my pathes. The lighters of this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle (ſayth Chriſoſt.) are the father the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſoſt. in cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Mat.</hi>
               </note> ſonne and the holy ghoſt. The candle ſticke is the Church: or euery godly man hauyng the word. By this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle the théefe or falſe teacher is eſpyed: ſo ſayth <hi>Theophilact.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lactus in Luc.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>It is called the bread of the ſoule: for that it feedeth the ſoule. Man ſhall not liue by bread onely, but by euery <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.</note> word that procéedeth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of God. A fiſhe can not liue without <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.</note> water, a ſhéepe can not liue without paſture, this mortall body ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not long endure without foode, the ſoule ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not long liue without the word of God. This is the meat of fayth.</p>
            <p>This word is light. The people that walked in darkneſſe haue ſene a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9. 1.</note> great light. This is conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 19.</note> light is come into the world, and men haue loued darknes rather then light, becauſe their déedes were euill. To giue light to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſit in darknes. &amp;c <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:25"/>
            <p> It is named water: Chriſt ſaid to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 12. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 55. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. <hi>Hier.</hi> 2. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 25.</note> woman of Samaria: if thou kneweſt the gift of God, &amp; who it is that ſayth to thée giue me drinke, thou wouldeſt haue aſked of him, &amp; he would haue geuen thée the water of life.</p>
            <p>It is a royall and kyngly feaſt. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is the ſword of the ſpirit. This ſword is very neceſſary to all that be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.</note> in this warfare. For who goeth to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.</note> battaile without a ſworde. Hee that hath no ſword let him ſell his coate and buy a ſword.</p>
            <p>The ſpiritual Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na. Gather your Manna while you haue tyme. The horne of ſaluation: The incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> ſéede whiche liueth and laſteth for <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Hier.</hi> 23.</note> euer: A ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer that breaketh the hard ſtone: A key that giueth entry into the houſe, which is the kyngdome of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. <hi>Origen. in num. Hom.</hi> 18. <hi>pag. vlt. Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 86. <hi>Luc.</hi> 5. <hi>Luc.</hi> 4. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note> of heauen: The ſcepter of the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: An arrow that pearceth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: A heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly trumpet: A net enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and bringyng vs together: The word of grace: The word of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: The word of reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation: The word of truth: The word of vertue: The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12269:25"/> word of lyfe euerlaſtyng: The word <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Ebtu.</hi> 2. <hi>Iac.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 39. 8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.</note> and way of righteouſneſſe: yea righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe it ſelfe: Grace and veritie: The wiſedome of God in a miſterie: That good word whereof Eſay ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: which is called good, for that it bringeth all goodneſſe: And (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) it is called the kyngdome of God: The kyngdome of God ſhalbe taken from you, and giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a nation bringyng forth the frutes therof.</p>
            <p>The premiſſes conſidered, I may ſay with the Prophet Hieremie, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hier.</hi> 22. 29</note> 
               <hi>terra, terra, audi verbum Domini:</hi> O thou earth, earth, earth, heare the word of the Lord. The fooliſhe carle Nabal ſtill carieth earth in his eyes, earth in his eares, and earth in his toung. Aboue all thynges he deſireth to ſée earth, to heare of earth, and to ſpeake of earth. Many Nabals, many carles, many fooles. But one thyng is neceſſary, one thyng is neceſſary, one thyng is neceſſary, &amp; that is the word of God. Mary hath choſen the good part, whiche ſhall not be taken away <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. <hi>vlt. verſ.</hi>
               </note> from her.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:26"/>
            <p> The firſt precept that Iſocrates gaue to prince Demonicus was τίμα τὸν θεό<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: feare God.</p>
            <p>The firſt law that ſhould be geuen to any man ſayth Plato, ſhould be to the encreaſe of godlynes.</p>
            <p>The chiefeſt oth which the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens toke, was this: <hi>Pugnabo pro fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris &amp; cum alijs &amp; ſolus.</hi> In defence of Religion I will fight, both in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and alone. Among the Atheniens no king was created, before he had taken orders and was a prieſt. They iudged the wiſeſt, beſt, and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned, to be fitteſt to offer ſacrifice to their Gods, to the great ſhame of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s now adayes, which thinck the moſt abiect &amp; outcaſt good inough, to take vpon him ſo high and holy a function. The auntient Romaines, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtinct of nature, thought ſo reuerently of religion, that they ſent their children, yea euen the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt men of Rome, ſent their ſonnes into <hi>Hetruria,</hi> to learne the ſeruice of God. Nowadayes a meane gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thinketh his childe to good, to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12269:26"/> learne and profeſſe true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is cleare and euident, what care heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men ignorant of the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God, haue had of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Poets by their feyninges haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended it, Oratours haue exhorted vnto it, Philoſophers haue thought it neceſſary in a common wealth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people haue ſworne to defend it, Noble men haue preferred it, Kinges haue profeſſed it. There is no religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without the word of God. We haue the vnderſtanding of the will of God by his onely word. For without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, our ſight is blindnes, our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ignorance, our wiſedome fooliſhnes, our deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuiliſhnes.</p>
            <p>The profite &amp; fruite of this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly word, is wonderfull. All ſcripture <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16</note> geuen by inſpiration of God, is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 4</note> to teach, to reproue, to correct, to inſtruct in righteouſnes, that we may be patient and finde comfort. S. Auguſt: ſayth, <hi>In ſcripturis didicimus Chriſtum, in ſcripturis didicimus Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 166.</note> In the ſcriptures we haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt, in the ſcriptures we haue
<pb facs="tcp:12269:27"/> learned the church. S. Baſill: ſayth, <note place="margin">Baſil. in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione: quod Deus non cauſa ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbum Dei ex quo ſolo noſcitur deus, regiam via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monstrat, &amp; est lucerna pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum nostrorum:</hi> The word of God by the which onely God is knowne, ſheweth the kinges highway, and is the light of our feete.</p>
            <p>We learne fayth in the ſcriptures. S. Hilary ſayth to the Emperour <note place="margin">Hilarius ad Imperat. Conſtant.</note> Conſtantinus: <hi>Fidem Imperator quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris? audi eam, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de nouis chartulis, ſed de dei libris:</hi> Doth your Maieſtie ſéeke the fayth? Heare it then, not out of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new ſchrolles, but out of the booke of God.</p>
            <p>S. Ambroſe ſayth, <hi>Chriſtus oritur</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ. in Hexam: lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>in lectione ſcripturarum ſol iuſticiae:</hi> In reading the ſcriptures, Chriſt the ſun of righteouſnes riſeth. To be ſhort, S. Auguſt: ſayth, <hi>verbo Dei docemur in omnibus:</hi> By the word of God wée are inſtructed in all thinges. All thinges neceſſary to ſaluation are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture: for profe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, (becauſe other matters call me awaye) I leaue briefly theſe places: Ioh: 14. 25. verſ. 2. Timo: 3. 15. Luc:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12269:27"/> 14. 17. Math: 22. 4. verſe. Eſai: 5. 4. verſe. This matter is proued out of the moſt auntient fathers: <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> read <hi>Irenaeus. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. and 4. <hi>Tertul. de praeſcript. haeres.</hi> As many as drincke of this heauenly fountayne, ſhall receiue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of it: the blind ſhall ſee, the deaf ſhall heare, the dumme ſhall ſpeake, the lame ſhall walke, fooles ſhall be wiſe, the ſicke ſhal be whole, the dead ſhall reuiue. The drincking of this fountayne, hath made many proud men, humble: many couetous miſers mercifull: many faythles, faythfull: many filthy fornicators, chaſt: many furious and wrathfull, méeke, and milde: many ſlouthfull and drouſie, vigilant and watchfull: many feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, bold: yea and euen contemners of Phalaris Bul: many Saules, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Paules: manye manye children of darcknes, the children of light. God by his worde, offereth to vs his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hand: by fayth we geue to God our hand: and the ſacraments are as a third hand, which confirme and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<pb facs="tcp:12269:28"/> the ioyning of the other two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. If you feare the iudgement of ſinne: This moſt pretious worde offereth you righteouſnes in Chriſt: if you feare death, it offereth lyfe: If you feare the fire of hel, it offereth the ioyes of heauen: and breefely, you haue in this word, whence you may take both in lyfe recreation, and in death preſeruation. Moyſes hauing the word of God, could diuide the ſea. The Apoſtles (although poore fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) with the worde of God ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the world. The blinde which heard the voyce of Chriſt, receiued ſight: The dombe ſpeach, wherewith they glorified God: the lame ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, which they applied to the ſeruice of God: the deaf hearing, whereby they became attentiue hearers of this gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious worde. Chriſt ſayd to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers daughter: Mayde ariſe, and ſhe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note> aroſe ſtraight waye. He ſayd to the widowes ſonne: young man I ſay to thée ariſe, and he that was dead ſat vp <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 7.</note> and began to ſpeake. And to Lazarus he cryed with a lowd voyce: Lazarus <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 11.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12269:28"/> come forth, &amp; he that was dead came forth, bound hand and foote. The te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtnous windes heard his voyce, and forthwith they were alayed: the ſea &amp; waues heard it, &amp; they became calme: men poſſeſſed with deuils heard it, and they obeied: yea the very deuils hearing his voyce, humbled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. O deaf and obſtinat mindes of wicked men: O you that lye groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the ground, and haue no fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thinges aboue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt crieth dayly. Damſell ariſe: young man I ſay to thee ariſe: Lazarus come forth: dead ſinner, embrace lyfe: But all are in a deepe ſléepe; a ſléepe of ſinne; and neglect to awake. Yet theſe miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men ought to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day will come, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day wil come when (wil they, nil they) they ſhall heare the voyce of the ſonne of God comming in the cloudes; with great power and maieſtie: Then ſhall they ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his iudgement ſeate. Then ſhall they heare to their endleſſe ſmart the thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of the law: depart from me ye curſed, into euerlaſtyng fier which is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 41.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:29"/> prepared for the deuils &amp; his angels.</p>
            <p>Heare therefore the word of God, while you haue tyme: Conſider the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> ſeaſon: it is now tyme to ariſe from ſléepe. It is now high tyme to heare: You haue no colour of excuſe. What more could haue bene done for the vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyard? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 5.</note> All thinges inuite, moue, and deſire you to heare. The clearenes of the holy Scriptures calleth you. For the Scriptures generally are eaſie &amp; cleare. So ſaith S. Paul: If our Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3.</note> be hid, it is hid to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are loſt. So ſayth the Prophet Oſeas: The <note place="margin">Oſeas vlt. cap. vlt. ver.</note> wayes of the Lord be ſtraight: but the wicked ſhall fall in them. So ſayeth the Prophet Dauid: The Scriptures <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.</note> are a candle &amp; a guide to our féete. So ſaith the old father Origene: <hi>Clauſum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen. in Exod. Hom.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>est negligent ibus, iuuenitur quare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus:</hi> If is ſhut from the negligent: but it is opened to them that ſéeke, &amp; knock for it. So ſayth <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Adhor. Ad Gentes. pagina.</hi> 63.</note> 
               <hi>Audite qui eſtis longe, Audite qui prope: nullis celatum eſt verbum, lux est communis, omnibus illuceſcit homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus. Nullus eſt in verbo Cimmerius,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12269:29"/> 
               <hi>festinemus ad ſalutem, ad regeneratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem:</hi> Hearken ye that be far of, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ye that be neare. The worde of God is hid from no man: It is a light common vnto all men: There is no darknes in Gods word. Let vs make haſt to ſaluation, to regeneration. So <hi>Fulgentius: <hi>In Scripturis diuinis abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat</hi>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Fulgentius in Serm. de Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; quod robustus comedat, &amp; quod paruulus ſugat:</hi> In the Scriptures of God there is plenty ſufficient, both for the ſtrong to eate, and for the litle one to ſucke. So <hi>Irenaeus: <hi>Scripturae in</hi>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iraeneus. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 31</note> 
               <hi>aperto ſunt, &amp; ſine ambiguitate, &amp; ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter ab omnibus audiri poſſunt:</hi> The Scriptures are playne, and without doubtfulnes, and may be heard indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly of all men. So ſayth Chriſoſt. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſoſt. in</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ. Hom.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Omnia clara &amp; plana ſunt in Scripturis diuinis: quaecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que neceſſaria ſunt, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festa ſunt:</hi> All thynges are cleare and plane in the holy Scriptures: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thyng is neceſſary for vs, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo manifeſt. So ſayth <hi>Epiphanius Lib.</hi> 2. So ſayth Saint Hierom. in Pſal. 86. So (to conclude) Gregory: ſayth <note place="margin">Greg. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrum.</note> it is a ſtreame wherin the litle lambe
<pb facs="tcp:12269:30"/> may wade, and the great Elephantes may ſwymme.</p>
            <p>But touchyng the diſcourſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, S. Ambroſe ſayth that, No creature in earth or in heauen, is able to reache to the depth of theſe thyngs. Theſe are his wordes: <hi>Mens</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ. ad Gratianum de fide. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>deficit, vox ſilet, non mea tantum ſed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelorum: ſupra poteſtates, ſupra ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, ſupra Cherubim, ſupra Seraphim, ſupra omne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſum eſt:</hi> The mynde is aſtonyed, the voyce fayleth, not onely of me, but alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angels: it is aboue the powers, aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angels, aboue the Cherubins, aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seraphins, &amp; aboue all maner of vnderſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtandyng all theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t properties of Gods word, and mo then a thouſand thouſand tounges ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> declare: We become Citizens of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razin, Bethſaida, and Capharnaum. Tyrus, Sido<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Sodom, the Quéene of the South, the men of Niniue, and that barbarous Eunuche, ſhall riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.</note> vs in the day of iudgement. If ſuch preachyng had bene in Tyrus &amp; Sidon, as hath bene in England (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12269:30"/> theſe xx. yeares): they would haue repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in ſackcloth and aſhes. Therfore it ſhalbe eaſier for Tyrus &amp; Sidon at the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for England. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mighty workes which haue bene done in England, had bene done among them of Sodom: They had remained without plague of fire and brimſtone. The Quéene of the South ſhall riſe againſt vs at the day of iudgement. A woman &amp; a Quéene, a frayle ſexe, the weaker veſſell, yet of Princely power: men the ſtronger veſſell, and yet moſt of them not of Princely power. She was a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: we are now <hi>Domestici:</hi> of the houſhold. She wanted the promiſes of Meſſias: we haue the promiſes of Meſſias. She came to Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wiſe man certainly, yet a mortall and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, whiche could not helpe her but in externall thynges, and therein peraduenture barely and ſlenderly: we refuſe to come to Chriſt God and man, who can helpe vs in all thyngs, who is all in all, and all to all. She came to heare the wiſedome of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon?
<pb facs="tcp:12269:31"/> Wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull was his wiſedome: his wiſedome exceeded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſedome of all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Eaſt, &amp; all the wiſedome of the Egyptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: he excéeded all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in wiſedome: he wrote iij. thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes. His ſonges were a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; fiue. He diſputed of trees, euen from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ceder trée that groweth in Libano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto the Iſop that ſpringeth out of the wall. And he diſputed of beaſtes, foules, wormes and fiſhes. There came of all nations to heare the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Salomon, &amp; from all kynges of the earth whiche had heard of his wiſedome. But behold he that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth this day out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhip, is greater then Salamon, and preacheth farre greater and better matters. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding fooles refuſe to heare his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng. This famous Quéene came to Salomon from far, &amp; out of a ſwéete, and frutefull countrey, the frutefull Arabia, called alſo Saba: ſo frutefull that it bringeth corne and fruite twiſe in the yeare, where groweth all kind of ſpices, and ſwéet gummes: and the Townes are vnwalled, becauſe the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12269:31"/> people do liue alwayes in peace. But we neglect to walke a litle way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walles of our Cities, &amp; to leaue ill ayre, ill ſoyle, ill company, ill exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, ill maners, to come to Chriſt. She came with great perill: we may come without perill, yet we come not. She left her happy kyngdome, &amp; with long and painful trauaile, came to Salomon: we haue Chriſt in the kyngdome of England, without lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of kyngdome, and with litle tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile may wee heare him: yet wee heare him not. She came with giftes: She came to Hieruſalem with a very <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reg.</hi> 10. 2. <hi>Paralip.</hi> 2. 9 <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 3.</note> great trayne, with Camels that bare ſwéet odours: &amp; gold excéedyng much, and precious ſtones. But wee may haue acceſſe to Ieſus Chriſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 55. 1.</note> without trayne, without gifts: Come to the waters all ye that be thirſty, &amp; ye that haue no money come buy. &amp;c. We refuſe grace offered fréely. This noble Queene knew Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fame: we know Chriſt by his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold miracles, &amp; yet we come not, yet we beleue not, yet we bring forth
<pb facs="tcp:12269:32"/> no good fruites. Therfore iuſtly ſhall we be condemned. It is ſhamefull to be vanquiſhed of a woman, more ſhamefull of an heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woman, moſt ſhamefull in ſuch a cauſe.</p>
            <p>The men of Niniue ſhall riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs and condemne vs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue vs of vnbeliefe: not by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, but by compariſon of the better act. They heard Ionas a very man: we reiect Chriſt God &amp; man. They heard Ionas a ſtraunger: we neglect to heare Chriſt a Sauiour, a father, a maiſter, a freind, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nuerſant with vs many yeares. They repented at the preaching of Ionas: we repent not at the preaching of Chriſt. Ionas preached but only thrée dayes: Chriſt hath preached moſt gratiouſly, and mercifully theſe Twenty yeares in England: and for all his ſo gratious and mercifull preaching, we repent not. Ionas wrought no miracle: Chriſt hath wrought many marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous miracles. He hath mightely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vs from Pharao of Egipt, from Nabuchadnazer of Babilon,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12269:32"/> from Holofernes of Syria, and hath miraculouſly preſerued Iudith of England, &amp; her people. For all theſe graces and giftes, wée are nothing thankfull: we are become carnall goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers: wée waxe colde in religion: the Papiſtes waxe whot, &amp; we waxe colde: I knowe it. We amend <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drabuli more,</hi> as ſower ale in ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: we become euery day worſe &amp; worſe.</p>
            <p>That barbarous Eunuche of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.</note> Queene of the Ethiopians, ſhall at the day of iudgement riſe agaynſt vs and condemne vs. He was an Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuche, floriſhing in authoritye, eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, &amp; riches: and yet for all that, in his iorney ſitting in his chariot, he read Eſaias the prophet. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he vnderſtode not what was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the prophet. He aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Philip not onely gentlely and courteouſly, (albeit he aſked him ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, vnderſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt:) but alſo deſired him, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he was clothed in poore attire,) that he would come vp and
<pb facs="tcp:12269:33"/> ſit with him in the chariot. You ſée the promptnes of his minde: you ſee the godly ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of a barbarous Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuche. Chriſoſt. largely and ſwéetely diſcourſing of this matter, in fine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth thus: <hi>Idoneus eſt barbarus iſte</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſoſt. in Gen. Hom.</hi> 35.</note> 
               <hi>qui nobis omnibus doctor fiat:</hi> This barbarous Eunuch, is méete to be a doctour and teacher to vs all.</p>
            <p>Sithence the caſe thus ſtandeth that we are wearye of ſpiritual Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, the beſt meate: and demeane our ſelues with the vnthankfull Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites vngratiouſly in heart, word, and worke againſt God and Moyſes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Anima nostra nauſeat ſuper cibo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 21. 5.</note> 
               <hi>iſto leuiſſimo:</hi> Our ſoule lotheth this light bread: we may aſſuredly loke to be plagued with the Iſraelites. God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 12.</note> is a righteous iudge, ſtrong and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and God is prouoked euery day. If a man will not turne, he wil whet his ſword, he hath bent his howe, and hath made it ready. He hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for him the inſtruments of death: he hath ordained his arrowes againſt the perſequtours. Behold the day is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. 11.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12269:33"/> come (ſayth the Lord) that I will ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a famine in the land: not a famine of bread, nor a thirſt of water, but a hunger, &amp; thirſt of hearing the word of God. And they ſhall wander from ſea to ſea: and from the North vnto the Eaſt ſhall they runne to and fro, to ſéeke the word of the Lord. In that day ſhall the fayre virgins, and the young men periſh for thirſt. He will alſo ſend famine of bread, peſtilence, fire, and ſword, he will ſend Tamer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, Nabuchadnazer, the hoſt of Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib, Titus and Veſpatian. The Syrians ſhall deuoure before, and the Philiſtines behinde. He will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.</note> murtherers, &amp; burne vp their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; (as Eſay ſayth) the leage which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28. <hi>d.</hi> 15. 18.</note> they haue made with death and hell, ſhall be diſanulled. He ſuffereth long, he is a patient God. It is ſayd that he hath leaden feete: but he hath iron handes. He commeth ſlowlye, but when he commeth he payeth home. Violatours, and contemnours, of Gods word alwayes haue bin puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. For this fault Adam and Eue
<pb facs="tcp:12269:34"/> were baniſhed out of Eden, a moſt fruitfull and delightſome garden, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> a valley of teares, miſerie, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitye, there to eate their bread with the ſweate of their face. The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of Noah were miſerablye <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.</note> drowned in the floud. The enemies of Lot were deſtroyed with brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> and fire. The Iſraelites were greuouſly puniſhed and plagued, as Moyſes and the Prophets in many places make mention. Dauid loſt <note place="margin">1. <hi>Paral. ca.</hi> 21.</note> ſeuenty thowſand men plagued with peſtilence. Abſolon was hanged, <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.</note> ſlayne, and caſt into a pit. Saule was ſore plagued, depoſed from his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 15. 18. <hi>and. laſt. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Paral.</hi> 10.</note> afflicted and vexed with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and finally ſlayne with his thrée ſonnes, his harnes bearer, and all his men, in one day. Sedechias was ſent <note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 25. 3. <hi>Ren.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Paral.</hi> 32. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. <hi>Act.</hi> 12. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 9.</note> into Babilon and made blinde. Robo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am the ſonne of Salomon, of twelue tribes loſt tenne. Sennacherib was ſlayne of his ſonnes. Pharao with all his chiualrie was drowned in the red ſea. Herod horriblely ended his lyfe. Ieſabel was caſt out of a window,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12269:34"/> and doggs did eate her. Ionas was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionae.</hi> 1.</note> caſt into the ſea. A certayne Prophet was killed by a Lyon. The children <note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2. 24</note> that mocked Eliſeus were torne of beares. Corazin, Bethſaida, and Caphernaum were curſed with woe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.</note> woe, and caſt downe to hell. That famous citie Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, named ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme the holye citye, was piteouſlye plagued, made euen to the ground <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Miche.</hi> 3. <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.</note> with the children within it, deſtroyed ſtick and ſtone, and turned to a heape of ſtones, for contemning the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mercifull viſitation: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting Chriſtes heauenly word, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and all his benefites. So Chriſt prophecied, and ſo it came to paſſe. For the ſame fault, (truely a horrible fault) the kingdome of the Romaines was deſtroyed, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chaldeans, the kingdome of the Macedonians, the kingdome of the Perſians, the kingdome of the Carthaginia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and many other moe. Paule preached to the Colloſſians, Hierapolians, and Laodiceans, but they conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned his wordes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:12269:35"/> (as Oroſius witneſſeth) the earth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oroſius. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> opened and ſwallowed them vp. O Hieruſalem Hieruſalem, thou that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.</note> killeſt the Prophets and ſtoneſt them which haue bene ſent vnto thée, how ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would I haue gathered thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren together, euen as a henne gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her chickens vnder her winges, and ye would not: behold, your houſe is left vnto you deſolate.</p>
            <p>O England england which conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt the word of god, and dealeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfully with them that are ſent vnto thée, hating them that rebuke <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 5. 10</note> thee in the gate, and abhorring them that ſpeake vprightly, how oft (ſayth Chriſt) woulde I haue gathered thy children together, as a henne gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her chickens vnder her winges, &amp; ye would not. Behold, your houſe ſhall be left vnto you deſolate, and the vineyard ſhall be let out vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.</note> huſbandmen, which ſhall yelde fruite in due ſeaſon: except ye ſpede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3</note> repent. For now is the Axe layd to the roote of the trée: and euery trée that bringeth not forth good fruite,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12269:35"/> ſhall be cut downe and caſt into the sire. Therefore know the tyme, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme the tyme while you haue time. The ſwallow knoweth her time: The Crane knoweth her tyme. The whery man taketh his tyde: The ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man his gale: The Smith ſtryketh whileſt the Iron is whot. The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman felleth his corne when it is ripe: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harueſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maketh haye whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſunne ſhineth: The ſower caſteth his ſéede, when the ground is melow. As yet the ſunne ſhineth, as yet is the acceptable tyme, as yet to day laſteth, as yet the gate is open, as yet grace is offered, yet the tyde ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and yet Chriſt cryeth by his preachers, Earth, earth, earth heare the word of the Lord. Therfore, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially conſidering the ſeaſon, after the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of this people, let vs with all indeuour and feruencye preaſſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſt, to heare his ſwéete and comfortable worde. Thus much for the firſt part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he ſtood by the lake of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezareth and ſawe two ſhyps ſtand</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:36"/> 
               <hi>by the lakes ſide: but the fiſhermen. &amp;c.</hi> The place is noted where theſe thinges were done. Mathew &amp; Marke call it the ſea of Galilee. It is called alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea of <hi>Tiberias.</hi> The place was pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and delectable, not without goodly paſtures. Nighe to the ſame were many goodly and populous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: as Capharnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Bethſaida, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razin, the regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ten Cities, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Egeſip. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>de excidio Hieroſo. Ioſephus. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>Belli Iudaici. Plin. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> the region of the Gadarenes. In theſe Cities he often taught, both in their Synagoges and houſes, as occaſion ſerued. You haue an elegant deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this place in <hi>Egeſippus, Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> and <hi>Plini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he ſaw two ſhyppes: but the fiſherme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were gone out of them, and were waſhyng their nets. They had now no hope at all to catche any fiſh: but God of his infinite mercy, doth often tymes, ſhew his power in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, when thynges are paſt all hope of good recouery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was entred into one of the ſhyppes, which belonged to Simon: he prayed him, that he would</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12269:36"/> 
               <hi>thruſt out a litle from the land. &amp;c.</hi> Behold the wonderfull humilitie of Chriſt, he might haue commaunded, but hee prayeth. For the earth is the Lordes and all that therein is, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the world, and they that dwel therein &amp;c. Learne humilitie of this <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.</note> Doctour of humilitie, the beſt doctour that euer was, who ſayth: Learne of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 29.</note> me: for I am méeke and low in hart. Whiche wholeſome counſaile that excellent &amp; learned diuine S. Auguſt. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Tom.</hi> 10. <hi>de verbis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Mat. ſermo.</hi> 10.</note> notyng ſayth: <hi>Ille ille cui omnia tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didit Pater. &amp;c:</hi> That: euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of kinges and Lord of Lordes, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſon of the euerliuyng God to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the father had geuen all thynges. &amp;c. ſayth not, learne of me to make the world: or to rayſe the dead: but to be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble &amp; méeke. O wholſome &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaile. O faithful doctour: humble Doctour, Lord, and Maiſter of mankind. He would not teach that he was not: he would not commaund that he him ſelfe did not. Conſider <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.</note> this you which with ill ſhepheards by force and cruelty gouerne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:37"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>And he ſate down and taught the people out of the ſhippe.</hi> Chriſt eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where and alwayes ſheweth him ſelfe a Sauiour, and is ſet forth vnto vs in the Goſpell, preachyng diuers and ſundry wayes: Walkyng on the land, ſittyng in the ſhyp, paynefully trauailyng by the way, ſittyng vpon the well, in the Synagogues, in the ſtréetes, in houſes, in wildernes, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hils. He healed the ſicke, he comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the afflicted.</p>
            <p>Doth not wiſedome crie: doth not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 8. 1.</note> vnderſtandyng put forth her voyce? She ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in the top of high places, by the way in the place of the pathes. She crieth at the gates of Cities, and at the entries of mens doores. Theſe thynges accordyng to the letter, are beſt ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, which preached the Goſpell publiquely, not onely in Synagogues, and temples, but alſo in other places where the people aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together.</p>
            <p>Vpon the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine he made that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note> excellent and paſſing Sermon, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Mathew.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12269:37"/>
            <p> In his iorneys he oftentymes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted with his aduerſaries, taught the multitude and his Diſciples ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t matters, &amp; confirmed his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. <hi>Luc.</hi> 17.</note> doctrine with wonderfull miracles.</p>
            <p>At the gate of the Citie Naim hee <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 7.</note> ſhewed him ſelfe, by rayſing the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes ſonne.</p>
            <p>In priuate houſes when he ſate at <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 7. <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.</note> the table, he gaue heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and would not ſuffer ſomuch as that tyme to paſſe without doyng good.</p>
            <p>When hee was but xij. yeares old, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 2. 42.</note> he ſate in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple among Doctours, hearyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and poſing them, ſo that all men which heard him, had him in maruailous admiration, for his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular wiſedome, and paſſyng vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng.</p>
            <p>He made many Sermons publik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.</note> and openly in the temple at Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</p>
            <p>When he was brought bounde to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18. 19.</note> Caiphas, and of him demaunded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng his Diſciples and doctrine: He aunſwered, I ſpake openly to the world, I euer taught in the Sinago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
<pb facs="tcp:12269:38"/> and in the temple, whether all the Iewes reſort, and in ſecret haue I ſayd nothyng. &amp;c. Briefly, in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he graciouſly ſought meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruct the people.</p>
            <p>He calleth all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he excludeth no man. They that were not entred in Muſike and Geometrie, were not admitted into Platoes ſchole: but the mercyfull goodneſſe of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, admitteth all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into his ſchoole, not excludyng euen children: He tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth all men out of the ſhyp, of what ſoeuer age, ſexe, ſtate or condition they be.</p>
            <p>Hee inſtructed Nicodemus fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt gently he entreated the Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.</note> albeit a Heathen man.</p>
            <p>Hee behaued him ſelfe mildly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.</note> the woman of Samaria, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng on the well. Notable ſinners he deſpiſed not.</p>
            <p>What kinde of diſſeaſe did he euer cry fie vpon, or turne his face from? He turned his mercifull face to Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, to men poſſeſſed with deuils, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12269:38"/> with bloudy flixes, diſſeaſed with palſie, and many other daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous maladies, and cured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. He <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. <hi>Marc.</hi> 10. <hi>Luc.</hi> 18.</note> commaunded infantes to be brought vnto him, agaynſt the will and minde of his Apoſtles. He taught that you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. <hi>Marc.</hi> 10. <hi>Luc.</hi> 18.</note> man, whiche demaunded what good thyng he ſhould doe, that hee might haue eternall lyfe. He reiecteth not the weake in fayth: but he inuiteth, allureth, &amp; deſireth all to come to him.</p>
            <p>You haue heard how wiſedome in this place, and in all places cryeth to all men. And at this day ſhe ſlacketh not to cry, and to put forth her voyce in England and many other places, by Preachers, by holy Scripture, by ſignes and wonders. What maters Chriſt taught in this place, I finde not expreſſed. A learned man ſayth: <hi>Nefas eſt quaerere quae in ſacris Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gualterus in</hi> 8. <hi>Rom.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non traduntur:</hi> It is wickedneſſe to ſearch thoſe thynges which are not taught in ſcripture. Thus much tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the letter.</p>
            <p>Foure things come to be obſerued in this miſtery: The ſea, Chriſt in the
<pb facs="tcp:12269:39"/> ſhyp, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people on the ſhore, &amp; the ſhyp it ſelfe. The ſea is an Image of the world: Chriſt is an image of true and ſincere teachers: The people on the ſhore, an image of hearers: &amp; the ſhyp, an image of the true Church.</p>
            <p>Touchyng the firſt: The ſea hath his name of bitternes: <hi>Iſidorus</hi> ſayth: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſidorus lib.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Etimolog.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Propterea Mare appellatum, quod eius aquae ſunt amarae:</hi> The ſea hath his name <hi>Mare</hi> in Latin, of the Latin worde <hi>Amarum</hi> which ſignifieth bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe the waters therof are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The ſea is very bitter: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng, to fiſhes nouriſhed in the ſame it ſauoureth ſwéetelye: Right ſo the world is very bitter, yet to world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men chiefly delighting in the ſame, it ſauoureth ſwéetely. But woe be to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 5. 20.</note> them which make ſowre ſwéete, and ſwéete ſowre: which call euill good, and good euill: whiche make darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes light, and light darknes. The ſea is bitter: the dealynges of the world are bitter. Pride is bitter, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is bitter, vſurie is bitter, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, fornication, coſenyng, ſwearyng,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12269:39"/> forſwearyng, deceitfull vilanie, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous treacherie, &amp; murther are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Theſe horrible and hatefull vices with many moe, ouerflow the world. The world is bitter.</p>
            <p>The ſea is inconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, it ebbeth and floweth: The world is inconſtant, it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth euery day. Some be borne, and ſome dye. Some be ſicke, &amp; ſome be whole. Some grow toward mans eſtate. Some drawe in age. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes commeth good tydynges, ſome tymes heauy. To day in fauour, to morow quite out of credite. To day a man, to morow none.</p>
            <p>The ſea is full of daungers: daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of windes, pirates, Mermaide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, rockes, quickeſandes, &amp; other daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. There are thynges creepyng in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 25.</note> both ſmall &amp; great beaſts. There is that Leuiathan whom God hath made to play therein. They that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 42. 24.</note> ſayle ouer the ſea tell of the perilles therof, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we heare it with our eares, we maruaile thereat. They that go downe to the ſea in ſhyps, and occupy by the great waters: they ſée
<pb facs="tcp:12269:40"/> the wordes of the Lord, and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the depe. They ſée as it were a thouſand deathes. In the ſea no reſt can be had. The world is full of dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: in the world a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deathes, in the world no reſt Daungers in the world more then in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea. The world hath tempeſtuous windes, Pirates, rockes, waues, Mermaidens, quicke ſandes, and many moe daungers the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can be numbred. Moe periſhe in the world, then in the ſea.</p>
            <p>The ſea is te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtuous: the world is tempeſtuous. If the ſea ſeme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo calme, yet looke for a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt: If the world ſéeme neuer ſo proſperous, it may looke for a tempeſt of aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. The world hath neuer long ſtode without ſtormes and tempeſtes. The caſe is cleare, and S. Ambroſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ. in</hi> 7. <hi>Luc. Cyp. de bono pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae.</hi>
               </note> them. <hi>Procellae mundi.</hi> Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes or ſtormes of the world. The ſame wordes hath S. Cyprian and many other. Here is te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt of euil tongues, tempeſt of lying, tempeſt of ſlaunder, tempeſt of aduerſitye, tempeſt of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, tempeſt of loſſe of frendes and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12269:40"/> good men: ſhaking and extreme tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of death, eternall tempeſt for the wicked in hell.</p>
            <p>The ſea is full of monſters: the world is full of monſters: the world is full of monſtrous men, not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the name of men. Some haue their faces in their féete, and their féet in their faces, as all fooliſh Nabals and couetous carles. But God gaue man a face to look vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thing euen the heathen Poet knew. Some haue many heads: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſerue many maiſters, pride, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, drowſines, murther, &amp;c: ſuch and ſo great vices raigne in them. Therefore haue they as many heads &amp; mayſters, as they haue luſtes and affections raigning in them. <hi>Qui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 34.</note> 
               <hi>facit peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruus est peccati:</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer committeth ſinne, is the ſlaue of ſinne. Some haue two tongues, as all flatterers and ſlaunderers. Some <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 18.</note> haue ſwordes in their lips: raylers, ill tonged perſons, blaſphemous wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. There is a generacion whoſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 30. 14</note> téeth are as ſwords, and their chawes
<pb facs="tcp:12269:41"/> as knyues. Of ſuch the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſpeaketh ſaying: whoſe téeth are <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.</note> as ſpeares and arrowes, and their tongue as a ſharpe ſword. Behold, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.</note> they ſpeake with their mouth, and ſwords are in their lips. Proud me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, couetous men, vſurers, drunkards, hereticks, blaſphemers, ſlaunderers, are monſters. The world therfore is full of monſters.</p>
            <p>The ſea caſteth out her dead to the ſhore: the world caſteth out, and baniſheth thoſe that are dead to the world, and doe not the workes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. S. Paule ſayth, we are made a <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 9.</note> gaſing ſtocke to the worlde: Truth ſayth: if ye were of the world, the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 19.</note> world would loue his owne: howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, becauſe ye are not of the world, but I haue choſen you out of the world: Therfore the world hateth you: truth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 20.</note> farther ſayth, yf they haue perſequ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, they will alſo perſecute you. The ſeruaunt is not greater then the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 2. 10.</note> Lord. The world ſayth: let vs op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the poore righteous, let vs not ſpare the widow, nor old man. let vs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12269:41"/> not regard the heads that are graye for age: let the law of vnrighteouſnes be our ſtrength, for the thing that is féeble is nothing worth: Therefore let vs defraud y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous, &amp; why? he is not for our profite: nay he is cleane contrary to our doinges, he checketh vs for offending agaynſt the law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius Firmianus</hi> ſpeaking of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactan. A. cephali cap.</hi> 11.</note> thend of this world ſayth: <hi>Si qui erunt boni, praedae, ac ludibrio habebuntur:</hi> If there remaine any good men at that tyme, they ſhall be counted a pray, a bootye, and a ieſting ſtock. Canſt thou not flatter? canſt thou not lye? canſt thou not play the hipocrite? ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thou not follow the facion and ſerue the ſtage? no. Then thou art no méete man to lyue in this world. Chooſe a few companions.</p>
            <p>The ſea is no place to make our continuall abode. For no man ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on the ſea, to tarye ſtil on the ſea, but ſpedely to paſſe ouer. This world is no place of continuall abode: for <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11</note> we are ſtraungers and pilgrimes: Here haue we no continuing Citye, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ebru.</hi> 13. 14</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:42"/> but we ſéeke one to come. Yet wee build ſtately, as though it were the tower of Babel. We ruffile mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly in apparell, as though our fraile bodyes ſhould neuer turne to duſt. We lyue ſenſuallye, as though there were no other heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: we gather gold and ſiluer gredely as though we ſhould alwayes néede to vſe the ſame. By this dealing it ſhould ſéeme wee are not ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers and pilgrims. The kinglye prophet Dauid ſaith. I am a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.</note> ſtaunger with thée, and a ſoiourner as all my fathers were. S. Auguſt. writing vpon that place, hath theſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 39.</note> wordes: <hi>Non ait ſicut omnes homines, ſed ſicut omnes patres mei: Non omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt fides, infideles non poſſunt dicere ſe in terra peregrinos:</hi> He ſayth not as all men, but as all my fathers: for all men haue not fayth. The faythles cannot ſay that they are ſtraungers and pilgrims vpon earth. Here then is their abode, they are Citizens of Babylon, not of the heauenlye Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. Notwithſtanding, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe, the faythleſſe worldlings
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12269:42"/> at the length ſhall finde, that they were ſtraungers and pilgrims, when with the glotonous cormorant in the torments of hell they ſhall crye in vayne for mercye. That riche man deſired a drop, which denyed a crome. And there are rich men to whome now I ſpeake: they be all one with the other in name, let them beware that they drinke not all of one cup with him.</p>
            <p>In the ſea are deuouring fiſhes, and the great fiſhes deuoure the litle fiſhes: In the world great men, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men deuoure and vndoe poore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here might often tymes ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth right. Here many take their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throte. Here Anacharſis may ſée Solons lawes lyke to cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>webs, which held faſt the litle flees, and let the great flées breake thorow them. Here, Socrates may laugh to ſée litle théeues truſt vp at tiburne, and great theeues without any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment liuing ſtill. Here Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus may wéepe to ſée vertuous men deſpiſed, and vitious men extolled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:43"/> Notwithſtanding, vertuous men be deſpiſed and deuoured of tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes: yet they lyue as Ionas liued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whales bellye. As dying, and behold wée liue <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9.</note> ſayth S. Paule.</p>
            <p>You ſée now how the ſea is an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the world, you ſée the ſea, you ſée the world. To ſpeake all in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me: The world is the kingdome &amp; courte of Sathan, a denne of théeues, a ſhop of lyes, a Babylon of ſectes, a wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes full of wild beaſtes, an Inne full of cuttbrotes, a cage of doltes, a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, an Egypt: A mother to the euil, a Stepdame to the good. Here is no place for godly men, here deuouring fiſhes deſtroy all, here all wicked crimes raigne, no religion, no fayth, no charitye: or very litle. Therefore let vs not loue the world, nor world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges: for he that loueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world hath not the loue of God in him: but let vs goe with Lot out of Sodome, with Abraham out of Chaldée, with the Iſraelites out of Egypt, with Chriſt from the Iewes, and with Paule from the Phariſies.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12269:43"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Chriſt taught out of the ſhip:</hi> He performeth his office, to the which he was ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his father into this world: and becauſe he had not a pulpet on the land, and the people preſſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him: he entred into a ſhippe, and taught vpon the ſea: for the office of Chriſt was to teach: He ſent me to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 61. 1.</note> preach good tidinges vnto the poore. By his example he teacheth vs to doe the dutyes of our vocations faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The type or figure declareth, that the functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them which preach the worde of God, is paynefull and full of perill. The world hateth the light of veritye. Woe be vnto me ſayth <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16</note> S. Paul if I preach not the Goſpell. It is daungerous to be ſilent, &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to ſpeake, if we ſpeake wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly, or if we be ſilent fooliſhly, wée offend God. If we ſpeake truely, and reproue diſobedience boldelye, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hatefull and odious to the moſt part of men.</p>
            <p>Truely if euer the office of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching hath bin ſubiect to oboloquie and euill report: it is now. The worlde
<pb facs="tcp:12269:44"/> hateth the light of veritye. In ſo great malice of the world, partely contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and partelye perſecuting the word of the goſpell, who can ſatiſfie or content all men? In old tyme there were but ſeuen wiſe men among the Greekes: and now there are not ſo many fooles among vs: for all of vs glorye of our wiſedome: euery head is full of wit, euery man will haue his owne way: Hearers are rather raſhe iudges, than fit and obedient ſchollars: and moſt of them, before they haue learned any thing, doo raſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne all thinges. S. Auguſt. ſayth: <hi>Tutior eſt diſcentis, quàm doce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis conditio:</hi> Salfer is the condition of him that learneth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth. I pray you good audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce let me heare your iudgements. How ſhould a man make an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Sermon, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in matter or forme? Som would haue the matter Catholique: Some Goſpel like: Some would haue alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether common places of Scripture decided: Some would haue vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede ſtil in the treatiſes of fayth &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12269:44"/> with inuectiues agaynſt the Maſſe, Purgatory, and ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Other would haue vs to launch into the déepes of predeſtination, ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne, free will, election, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation. Other would haue vices rebuked: but they can not agree how it ſhould be done. Some would haue it generally and coldly: Some direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hotely: Some the vices of the Clergy and Magiſtrates: &amp; ſome one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the vices of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people and inferiours: all men, other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vices: but no man his owne vices. Theſe diſagrée in matter very ill, &amp; in forme much worſe. Some would haue long texts: ſome ſhort textes. Some would haue Doctours, Fathers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels: ſome call y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doctrine. Some would haue it ordered by Logicke: ſome terme that mans wiſedome. ſome would haue it poliſhed by Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otrique: ſome call y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perſuaſibleneſſe of wordes. And agayne in Rhetoricke ſome would haue it holy eloquence, liable to the Ebrue &amp; Gréeke phraſe: Some would haue it proper and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng to the Engliſh capacitie. Some
<pb facs="tcp:12269:45"/> loue ſtudy and learnyng in Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: Some allow onely a ſudaine motion of the ſpirite. Some would haue all ſaid by heart: ſome would haue oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe made to the booke. Some loue geſtures: ſome no geſtures. Some loue long Sermons: ſome ſhort Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. Some are coy and can broke no Sermons at all. But we be not to féede mens humours, but to folow Chriſt: we muſt folow Chriſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhyp, and the croſſe muſt be borne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of Chriſt. No man <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.</note> ſought more the glory of God then Chriſt: &amp; yet for all that, he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a blaſphemer. He liued without <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.</note> ſpot of vice, and yet he was called a wine bibber. Hee expreſly taught to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Luc.</hi> 20. <hi>Luc.</hi> 23. 2.</note> render to Ceſar the thynges whiche belong to Ceſar: and yet he was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to haue taught the contrary. No <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</note> man taught patience more: and yet <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</note> was he condemned as a ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon. There was neuer ſuch a one in Iſraell as Chriſt was in workes and wordes: Neuer any liued ſo purely: neuer any taught ſo heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly: and yet many wicked &amp; graces perſons ſayd
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12269:45"/> of him: he hath a deuill and is mad, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 10</note> why heare ye him? The ſchollar is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> not aboue the maiſter. You ſée the chaire of the maiſter: know the chaire of the ſchollar.</p>
            <p>More ſafe and ſure is the ſtandyng of the hearers, whiche ſtandyng on the land heare the word of ſaluation. The greateſt part of hearers kéepe them ſelues out of perill: for when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſudaine ſtorme of perſecution ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for the Goſpell on the ſea of this world: either they hide them ſelues: or els vtterly forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhip, chaire, teacher and all. Such is the condition of the moſt part of hearers. Theſe thyngs are clearely knowne. I neede not to make long demonſtration. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples remaine freſh in memory.</p>
            <p>Touchyng the ſhyp, the ſtate of the Church militant is here excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depainted. The Church of Chriſt is that ſhyp where agaynſt Sathan bloweth out ſo many blaſtes: the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man clothed with the ſunne, whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.</note> old Dragon ceaſeth not continually to perſecute. This ſhyp is like to the
<pb facs="tcp:12269:46"/> Arke of Noah. Euen as a ſhyp on the ſea whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſtormy tempeſtes ariſe, is terribly ſhaken: right ſo nothing in the waſt and wide world is more ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſtormes and tempeſtes of all maner euils, then the Church. If you aſke me who they are that ſhake the ſhyp of Chriſt, and how the ſame is ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I will giue you to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: Turkes, Iewes, Anabaptiſtes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, Sectaries, Atheiſtes, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, the Familie of loue, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhe rable, and to be ſhort the deuill and all his members ſhake this ſhyp: but they ſhal neuer be hable to drown it: For the gates of hell ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18.</note> agaynſt it. Becauſe Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the ſterne and hath the helme in his owne hand.</p>
            <p>For that the Romiſh Catholickes do moſt ſhake the true Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland which is the Church of Chriſt: I purpoſe at this preſent to proue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. They ſay they ſhake not the ſhip, but are in the ſhip as in the Arke of Noah: and that we Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes ſhake the ſhip, and are out of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12269:46"/> the ſhip, and out of the Arke. Farther they boldly ſay, that without the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their body, and their head the Churche of Rome, and their holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, no man can be ſaued. I will clearely proue the contrary: namely, that they ſhake the ſhip, that they are out of the ſhipp: and they are not the true Church. Their body is a Sinagogue of Sathan: their holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not head of the true Church: (happy were he if he were a member of the ſame) he hath not the keyes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottomles pit.</p>
            <p>I proue thus: the Romiſh Church heareth not the voyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepheard: Therfore the Romiſh Church is not the true Church. I wil proſecute this Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in treatyng of breakyng the net. Now to proue that they ſhake the ſhip, &amp; how. The Romiſh Church is a perſecutyng Church, therfore it ſhaketh the ſhyp, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true church. For perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident token of Antichriſtes Church. Cayn perſecuted Abell: the Giantes Noah: the Sodomites: Loth: Iſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,
<pb facs="tcp:12269:47"/> Iſaac: Eſau, Iacob: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Egyptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the Iſraelites: Pharao, Moſes: Saul, Dauid: &amp; yet Dauid would not hurt him. Of whom we learne that Gods Church doth ſuffer, rather than hurt: and pardon rather then perſecute. The falſe Prophetes perſecuted the true Prophetes. The Prieſtes, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, Byſhops, Annas, Herod, Pilate, and Caiphas, perſecuted Chriſt. The Iewes and Turkes, perſecute the Chriſtians: And moſt of all the tyran of Rome, perſecuteth Chriſtes litle flocke and congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Church of Chriſt did neuer perſecute, but was alwayes perſecuted. So <hi>Hilari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> &amp; <hi>Nicephorus</hi> in many places diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſayth excellently <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactan. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. Inſtitu. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> to this matter: <hi>Defendenda religio eſt, non occidendo, ſed monendo: non ſaeui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſed patientia: non ſcelere, ſed fide. Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi ſanguine &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis, ſi malo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defendere velis: ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non defendetur illa, ſed polluetur at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> violabitur:</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, not with murthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring, but with moniſhing, not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, but with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: not with fury,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12269:47"/> but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faythfulneſſe. For if ye defend Religion with bloudſhed and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, or with workyng of miſchief: It is not defended, but defiled, and diſteined. Chriſoſt. ſayth: <hi>Quem vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſoſt. in opere Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. Hom.</hi> 19. <hi>Tertul. in Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſanguine gaudente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lupus eſt.</hi> Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou ſéeſt delight in bloud, he is a wolfe. <hi>Tertul.</hi> ſayth: it is not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that a ſpirituall matter ſhould be tormented with temporall fire. Doth not the Pope perſecute all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? Is not his armes a rauenyng wolfe? his ſentence Burne, Burne, Burne? his badge, let vs lay waite for bloud? his head, blaſphemie? his ſhield tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? his breſt, iniurie? his eyes, fire? his girdle, fornication? his breath, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? his toung, the ſtyng of death? his féete ready to ſhed innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud? his ſword, violence? his croſſe, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? his pardons iniquitie? his triple crowne preſumption? his keyes, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition? and all his doyngs abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Him do folow great ſwarmes of Cainites, Gyantes, Sodomites, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians, Bailites, Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacheribbes, Scribes, Phariſeis, Herodians,
<pb facs="tcp:12269:48"/> Monkes, Friers, Cardinals, Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Idolaters, Paraſites, Poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Pardoners Bawdes, with all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſhe rable. Theſe are the right Canibals, like to the barbarous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of America y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eat one an other. Yet they ſay all this is for loue. A gentle kind of loue, like the loue of one Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippides, who tooke a cudgell and dyd <note place="margin">Ariſtopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis.</note> beate his father, and all for loue. But we may ſay with <hi>Tertullian: Crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas veſtra noſtra gloria eſt:</hi> Your cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is our glory. For Gods Religion, the more it is preaſſed, the more it encreaſeth.</p>
            <p>The congregation of Chriſt are <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.</note> called ſhéepe. A ſhéepe hath neither hoofes, nor ſharpe téeth, as wolues, Lyons, and Beares haue. Chriſt ſaid to his diſciples: Behold, I ſend you <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.</note> forth as ſhéepe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mids of wolues: he ſayth not as wolues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mids of ſhéepe. They are the true Churche <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. 22</note> of whome it is ſayd: for thy ſake are we ſlayne continually, and counted as ſhéepe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaughter. The marks of the true Church are theſe: the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12269:48"/> voyce of heauenly doctrine: the right vſe of the ſacraments: the croſſe: and obedience to the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the word. S. Auguſt. ſaith: <hi>Crux</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. de tempore. Serm.</hi> 130.</note> 
               <hi>regni inſigne eſt:</hi> The croſſe is the cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance or bagde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church. Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius ſayth: <hi>Caedi, Christianorum propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt: Caedere autem Chriſtianos, Pila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Athan ad ſolit vitam agentes.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; Caiphae officia ſunt.</hi> To be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, belongeth to Chriſtians: but to perſecute the Chriſtians, belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the office of Pilate, and Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas.</p>
            <p>The true Church is ſtill perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and neuer perſecuteth. Did the Patriarches perſecute? did the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets perſecute? did Chriſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute? did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles perſecute? when the Samaritanes would not receyue Chriſt, Iames and Iohn being as yet <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 9. 54.</note> nouices in Chriſtes ſchole, called for fire from heauen, and would haue burned and conſumed the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes: but Chriſt rebuked them ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: you wot not of what maner of ſpirite you are: for the ſonne of man is not come to deſtroy mens liues,
<pb facs="tcp:12269:49"/> but to ſaue them. Our weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (ſayth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 14. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4</note> S. Paule) are not carnall, but ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. Whereas it is obiected: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to come in: I aſke: what is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.</note> the power of the Church to compell? is it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of the outward ſword, or of the ſpirituall worde? Is it with the power of fire and fagot? Ought men to be violently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to fayth? It is euident and cleare, that Chriſt did not inſtitute in his kingdome, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forcible or worldly kind of gouern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment: for he ſayd: <hi>Regnum meum non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18. 36.</note> 
               <hi>eſt de hoc mundo:</hi> My kingdome is not of this world. Hath Chriſt euer bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 42. 3.</note> a bruſed réede? hath he euer quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the ſmoking flaxe? hath he not taught vs to pray for our enemies, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 44.</note> and for thoſe that perſecute vs? The Apoſtles vſurped not the ſword, to compell men to the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt. Can the Pope or any of his Prelates put faith into a mans hart by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? was any man compelled agaynſt his will, to the building of the outward <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.</note> tabernacle: &amp; ſhall any man be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to the building of the inward
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12269:49"/> tabernacle? Is not the mariage ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, the ſupper ſpirituall? Then muſt men be compelled with a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall weapon, which is with the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word. Not by hoſtes of men, nor by force of worldly ſtrength, but by my ſpirite, ſayth the Lord of hoſtes. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 4. 6.</note> So Peter compelled many to the fayth. It is the word of God, that maketh a man a new creature. <hi>Ergo</hi> neither ſword, nor fier. If the ſoule of man be a ſpirite, then muſt it be fed with ſpirituall foode, moued to faith by ſpiritual inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, drawne by the worde, led by the ſpirite, and perſwaded by the ſcriptures, whiche are the onely meanes which God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth. If an hereticke hold an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he holdeth it either of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or wilfulnes. If of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: he is to be conuerted by doctrine, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced by ſcripture, reformed by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, reduced by reaſon, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by the truth: If of wilfulnes, he is to be menaced by the law, and corrected by excommunication. It is written in a certaine learned treatiſe
<pb facs="tcp:12269:50"/> agaynſt the late of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel Tride<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſimum eſt omnes haereſes tantùm spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituali gladio verbi Dei iugulatas eſſe:</hi> Moſt true it is, that all hereſies are conuinced, onely with the ſpirituall ſword of the word of God. The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell (ſayth Damaſcenus) was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſc.</hi> 3. <hi>Sent. cap.</hi> 32</note> throughout all the world, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, armour, or battaile: by a few naked, poore, vnlearned, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted men, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded the wiſe of the world.</p>
            <p>Chriſt compelled Paule: If thou be Chriſt that ſo obiecteſt this: I pray thée compell the Turke, &amp; the Pope, which blaſpheme Chriſt. If thou art not Chriſt ſuffer. We ought to ſpare me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to pray for their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this matter you may reade more in Auguſt. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 107. 158. 160. 204. <hi>Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>contra Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co. Grammat. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 50. <hi>contra li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras Petiliani lib.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; cap</hi> 83. <hi>&amp; cap. vlt.</hi> and alſo in Chriſoſt. <hi>de anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate. Tom.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Compell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come in: Compell them. <hi>Quoad media:</hi> as in reſpect of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12269:50"/> the meanes, to wit, the meanes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed. Compell Remiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques to come to the Church. So S. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 204.</note> Auguſt. would haue the Donatiſtes compelled. Fayth commeth by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and many haue bin conuerted from infidelitye to fayth, from Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme to Chriſtianiſme, from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh rable to the Chriſtian congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, by that meanes. Seing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that perſecution is a note of the Church of Antichriſte, and that the Church of Roome perſecuteth: it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident that that Church ſhaketh the ſhip and is malignant.</p>
            <p>Out of the arke of Noah, that is, out of the Church, which is the body of Chriſt: no man is ſaued. That is moſt certayne: but that is not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the vnitie of the bodye in it ſelfe: but in reſpect of the vnitye of the whole bodye with the head, which is Chriſt. Read Chriſoſt. vpon the Epiſtle to the Colloſ. Homi. 7. It may pleaſe thoſe men to thinke vpon theſe thinges, which tranſfere this neceſſitye of vnitye, to the Church of
<pb facs="tcp:12269:51"/> Roome, and to their Byſhop the head thereof, the aduerſary of Chriſt, and vtter enemy to his croſſe: boldly bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and bragging, that out of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of this bodye and head of theirs, no man can be ſaued. For theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable men ought to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that this neceſſary vnitye, without which no man can haue ſaluation, is not that vnitye whereby members are ioyned to members, bunches to bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, monſters to monſters, and the deceiued to Antichriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deceiuer: but that it is that vnitye wherby the true members of the true bodye, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to the true and onely one head Ieſus Chriſte, our mediator and Sauiour.</p>
            <p>The tyranne of Roome is not the head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true church: I proue thus. He hath not the worde of God for his warrant. <hi>Ergo,</hi> he is not the head of the true church.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſayth that he himſelfe is the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.</note> onely vniuerſall Shepheard. The prophets haue propheſied ſo of Chriſt <hi>Eſai.</hi> 40. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37. 34. <hi>Hierem.</hi> 30.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12269:51"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle ſo nameth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ebru.</hi> 13. 20</note> him. Chriſt himſelfe not long before <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 16.</note> he left this world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſayd to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: I will pray the father, and he ſhall geue you another co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forter, that he may abide with you for euer, euen the ſpirite of truth. Here we learne what vicar Chriſt hath ſubſtituted: Not the Pope, but the holy ghoſt. So writeth <hi>Tertul.</hi> Barnard, and others.</p>
            <p>This place of Iohn, I am the good ſhepheard: S. Auguſt. expoundeth of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Ioh. Tract.</hi> 47. <hi>Chriſoſt. in Ioh. Hom.</hi> 59.</note> Chriſt. So doth Chriſoſt. So doth <hi>Nicholas Lyra</hi> as ſimple an interpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour as he was: <hi>Fiet vnus pastor, id eſt Christus:</hi> There ſhalbe one ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard: that is to ſay, not the Pope, but Chriſt. The Apoſtles had no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this monſtrous head. The Nicene Councell knew it not. The Councell of Carthage excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated &amp; curſed him to the deuill, that called him ſelfe vniuerſall Byſhop or chief Prieſt. The whole Councell of Aphrica conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the attempt of this vſurped iuriſdiction, and called it the ſmokie pride of the world. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
<pb facs="tcp:12269:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> Prelate doth ſubuert, corrupt, &amp; prophane the doctrine of Chriſt and his Sacraments, &amp; manifeſtly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth Idolatrie: Therfore he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be the vniuerſall Shepheard. He is not worthy to be called a Shepheard. A Shepheard? nay, a fleaſhéepe: A Byſhop? a Butcher: a Paſtour? a Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: a Prelate? a Pylate: a Vicar of Chriſt? a Vicar of Venus: a Cephas? Caiphas. Phocas that execrable mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therer, was he that firſt proclaimed the Byſhop of Rome to be head of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Platin. in vita Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facii.</hi> 3.</note> vniuerſall Church, about vj. hundred &amp; xiij. yeares after Chriſt was borne. This Phocas beyng but a common ſouldiour, did by treaſon and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie lay hands vpon his liedge Lord and Maiſter the Emperour <hi>Mauriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and in cruell ſort did him to death: and ſo by trayterous vilanie, he aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Empire. The maner of his crueltie was this: Firſt he commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded foorth the Emperours yongeſt ſonne, and cauſed him to be ſlayne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the fight of his father: and ſo the ſecond: and then the third: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde the Empreſſe. <hi>Mauritius</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:12269:52"/> heauely lookyng on lamentyng &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto God: Righteous art thou O Lord, and rightfull is thy iudgement. Laſt of all, he vſed the like tyranny alſo vpon the Emperour, and layd him, his wife and his iij. children on a heape together. After that he had thus liued and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſundry murthers and other great miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>: the people tooke him, ſlue him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ew him in to the fire. Here you ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motour, a holy promotour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes holynes: A murtherer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e finder out of ſupremacie: And Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>cie fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and builded vpon murther.</p>
            <p>S. Cyprian calleth <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Biſhops of Rome, brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and companions. And whereas cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Schiſmatickes yelded them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſubiect to the Byſhop of Rome, perſwading them ſelues that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Aphrica had leſſe power the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Byſhops of Rome: Cyprian cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them deſperate &amp; wicked perſons for ſo doyng. I frame this Argument out of Chriſoſt: <hi>Quicunque deſydera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſoſt. opene im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. Ho,</hi> 35.</note> 
               <hi>primatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in terra: in Coelo inueniet</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:53"/> 
               <hi>confuſionem:</hi> Whoſoeuer ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye deſireth ſupremacy vpon earth ſhall finde in heauen confuſion. The Byſhop of Roome ambitiouſlye deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſupremacye on earth: Therefore he ſhall finde confuſion in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Pope is Antichriſt: <hi>Ergo</hi> he is not the head of the Church. He which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.</note> himſelf aboue all that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God, is Antichriſt: The pope doth ſo: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Pope is Antichriſt. <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irenae. lib.</hi> 5 <hi>cap. penult.</hi>
               </note> a moſt auncient doctour of the Church, who liued almoſt fiften hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares ſince, diſputyng of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſayth thus: <hi>Antichriſtus cum ſit ſeruus, tamen adorari vult vt Deus:</hi> Antichriſt notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he be but a ſlaue, yet he will be worſhipped as if he were God. <hi>Ioachimus Abbas</hi> ſaith <hi>Antichriſtus iam pridem natus eſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, &amp; altiùs extolletur in ſede Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica:</hi> Antichriſt is long ſince borne in Rome, yet ſhall he be higher aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Apoſtolick ſea. Antichriſt (ſayth Gregory) is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall clayme <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gregor. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 38.</note> to himſelfe to be called the vniuerſall Byſhop, and ſhall haue a garde of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12269:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> prieſtes to attend vpon him. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei. lib.</hi> 18. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17.</note> ſayth, Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the firſt Roome, and Rome the ſecond Babylon. And to come nearer the matter, S. Iohn ſayth, Antichriſt ſhall ſit in the Citye that is built vpon ſeuen hilles, and ſo is the Citie of Roome. And Sybilla ſayth that the greateſt terror, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of his Empire, and the greateſt woe that he ſhall worke, ſhall be by the bankes of Tyber: and there is Roome. He that hath eyes to ſée, let him ſee: &amp; he that hath eares to heare, let him heare.</p>
            <p>Agayne Chriſt was humble, the Pope proude: Chriſt was poore, the Pope rich: Chriſt patient, the Pope impatient: Chriſt merciful, the Pope vnmercifull: Chriſt vſed admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Pope impriſonment: Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, the Pope extirpation: Chriſt all manner of clemencie, the Pope all manner of tyranny: briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you ſhall finde the Pope in all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſeuered from Chriſt: you ſhall finde him to Chriſt, Beliall: to light, darcknes: to truth, falſhode. Are not
<pb facs="tcp:12269:54"/> theſe, and ſuch lyke, the very fruites of Antichriſt? the trée is knowne by his fruite.</p>
            <p>Whereas theſe ſhakers of the ſhip of Chriſt vrge <hi>Antiquitie, Vniuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litye,</hi> and <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> to make much for them: I aunſwere theſe thinges make nothing for them, but rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them. Notwithſtanding their Vincentius Lirinenſis whome they haue in ſo high price. This is Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius pretious aſſertion <hi>In ipſa ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vincen. li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinen. pro Catholicae fidei anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitate in cap. lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia magnopore curandum eſt, vt id teneamus quod vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, quod ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, quod ab omnibus creditum eſt:</hi> In the Catholick Church we muſt haue eſpeciall care, to hold that which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, alwayes, and of all men is beléeued. Yet to helpe his credite the Church of Roome was not ſo defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hereſies at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time when he did write, which was a thouſand yeares &amp; more ſince, as it is mentioned. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitye</hi> doth not preiudice or hinder trueth. Their antiquity is no marke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church. Their <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitye. <hi>Tertull.</hi> ſayth, nothing can <note place="margin">Tertull. de virginibus velan.</note>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:12269:54"/> preſcribe agaynſt truth, neither time, nor authoritye of perſons, nor priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges of kingdomes. And a litle after he ſayth: Chriſt is called trueth, and not cuſtome: If Chriſt be from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, and more auntient than all: then is alſo trueth more auntie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t than all cuſtomes. Hereſies haue alwayes bin vanquiſhed by truth, and not by noueltye, and whatſoeuer is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this trueth, is hereſie, though it be neeuer ſo olde a cuſtome. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. ſayth, after that the truth is once found out, let cuſtome geue place to the trueth: let no man ſet cuſtome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truth &amp; reaſon: for reaſon &amp; truth euermore put cuſtome to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. That ſwéete martyr S. Cypri. ſayth: <hi>Si ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyp. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>Pag.</hi> 39.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtus andiendus eſt: non debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus attendere quid aliquis ante nos fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendum putauerit, ſed quid qui ante omnes eſt Chriſtus prior fecerit. Neque enim hominis conſuetudinem ſequi opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, ſed Dei veritatem:</hi> If Chriſt be onely to be heard: we muſt not regard what any other hath done before vs, but we muſt looke what Chriſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:12269:55"/> done, which is before al. For we muſt not follow the cuſtome of men, but the truth of God.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, Ignatius a diſciple to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius ad philadelph. Canon. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetud. diſt.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> S. Iohn the Euangeliſt and a moſt conſtant martyr of Chriſt, hath theſe wordes: all my <hi>Antiquitie</hi> is Ieſus Chriſt, whome not to heare is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt deſtruction. You ſee the moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſend vs to learne the truth of him which is moſt auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of all. <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> diſputyng with S. Ambroſe agaynſt the certaintie of the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Religion, groundeth his chief Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon antiquitie: Affirmyng the Religion (in truth the ſuperſtition) of the Heathen to be the truer. Becauſe it had bene of more antiquitie. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Ambroſe ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth almoſt graueled. But the very <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 46. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24. 27.</note> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere to be made hereunto is that the Religion of the Heathen is not more auncient than ours, much leſſe the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Papiſtes. Our true Chriſtian Religion was not firſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed xv. hundred fifty &amp; odd yeares ſithence, when Chriſt and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12269:55"/> taught that moſt playnly in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But from the firſt infancie of the world immediatly after the creation of the firſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame hath bene ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly reuealed, and from that time forward alwayes hath bene confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the teſtimonies of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, Patriarkes, Apoſtles, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerued and maintained by all the godly of all ages euen from Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this houre.</p>
            <p>For all this I will not ſticke to graunt theſe men antiquitie euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nemrod, yea to pleaſure them from Cain. Their Babylon bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Cain. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 64. <hi>Tom.</hi> 8.</note> They alwayes turne the bewtie of Sion into the confuſion of Babylon.</p>
            <p>Vniuerſalitie is no true note of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church: Chriſt clearely teacheth, that many more ſhalbe damned than ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: becauſe that fewe doe heare the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>Mar.</hi> 4. <hi>Luc.</hi> 8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 13.</note> word of God, and bryng forth fruites through patience. Many are called, and fewe are choſen. Enter ye in at the ſtraite gate. For wyde is the gate and broad is the way, that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be which
<pb facs="tcp:12269:56"/> goe in thereat: but ſtraite is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth vnto lyfe, and few there be that finde it. Chriſt ſayth feare not, my litle <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 12. 23</note> flocke. &amp;c. In the time of the flud, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viij. perſons: Noah and his familie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.</note> were preſerued in the Arke. At the burnyng of Sodome and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> adioynyng, Loth, his wife and ij. daughters were ſaued: and yet after Lothes wife (becauſe ſhe looked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynd her,) was turned into a piller of ſalt. Of the innumerable multitude <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.</note> of the children of Iſraell, and others which went out of Egypt toward the land of promiſe: onely Caleb and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſua entred into that fruitfull land, and all the other periſhed miſerably in the wildernes. In the dayes of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. <hi>Baal hath moe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets then God.</hi>
               </note> iiij. hundred and fifty Prophetes of Baal, and iiij. hundred Prophetes of the groues which did eate at Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels table, ſtode agaynſt <hi>Elias.</hi> Foure hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred falſe Prophetes ſtode agaynſt <note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg:</hi> 22.</note> one true Prophet <hi>Michaea.</hi> The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed doctrine of Chriſt him ſelfe hath not bene receiued euermore, euery
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12269:56"/> where, &amp; of all men. For the Turkes receiue it not, the Iewes abhorre it, the Church of Rome abuſeth it. The vniuerſall conſent of the world, ſtode againſt the Diſciples of Chriſt a few poore Fiſhermen: and they all (except Iohn the Euangeliſt) were cruelly done to death. Conſider the tyme of Iohn Huſſe a man of exquiſite, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent learnyng, matched with holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of lyfe. He preached the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt ſincerely: concernyng iuſtification and the true Church. &amp;c. Therefore the malignant rable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced him an hereticke in the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell of Conſtance, excommunicated him, painted deuils on his cap, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and burned him, and beyng conſumed to aſhes threw the ſame in to a riuer. All this was done by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſent. After this vilanie, they triumphed for that they had diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched him. The ſaying of Chriſt is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 16. 10.</note> true: the world ſhal reioyce. But ſuch ſpectacles are mournefull to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and cauſe them to ſhed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 16. 20.</note> bitter teares: ye ſhall wéepe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb facs="tcp:12269:57"/> The bones of <hi>Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Phagius,</hi> thoſe learned, godly, and faythfull ſouldiours of Chriſt, were burned at Cambridge with <hi>Salue fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta dies:</hi> in a ſolemne Proceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Was not this, <hi>Iugulare mortuos?</hi> To kill (as they ſay) God haue mercy on his ſoule? <hi>Athanaſius</hi> that learned and godly Byſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſtode al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt againſt all the world, beyng for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with the truth. <hi>Paphnutius</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſtode agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of Nice and was heard. Chriſt mercyfully <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 17.</note> cured x. leapers: and of them, onely one returned and gaue glory to God. Hath not our Sauiour prophecied that many falſe Chriſtes &amp; falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> ſhall ariſe, and deceiue many in the laſt caſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world? How goeth the world now? The holy father in the Councell of Trent pronounceth thus: <hi>Qui docet fide in Chriſtum nos tantum iuſtificari abſque operibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris: item certo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credendum eſſe remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem peccatorum, ſit anathema:</hi> He that teacheth that we are iuſtified one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by fayth in Chriſt, without our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12269:57"/> owne workes: and alſo that we ought to beleue aſſuredly that our ſinnes are forgiuen vs: let him be accurſed. O curſed and peſtilent Councell.</p>
            <p>Touching the Catholique church, S. Auguſt. writeth thus: It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>de Gen. ad lit. cap.</hi> 1.</note> calleth <hi>Catholica: Quia vniuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter perfecta est &amp; in nullo claudicat: &amp; per totum orbem diffuſa eſt:</hi> Becauſe ſhe is vniuerſally perfect, and halteth in nothyng (nor is ſhut vp in any one countrey as was the Church of the Iewes,) but is diſperſed throughout the whole world. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> writeth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiphan. contra hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſes Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. 321<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> that in the reigne of Diocletian and Maximinian (a tyme of great perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution) <hi>Meletius</hi> Byſhop of Thebais in Egypt and Peter Byſhop of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, and diuers other godly men were put in priſon in Alexandria the chief Citie of Egypt. Of whom, ſome ſuffered Martyrdome: and ſome refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Martyrdome: They that remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aliue in priſon: diſputed whether they that had reuolted through the violent perſecution ſhould be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued agayne into the Church, or no.
<pb facs="tcp:12269:58"/> The chief of theſe in the diſputation, were Peter and <hi>Meletius: Petrus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia motus:</hi> ſayth <hi>Epiphanius:</hi> Peter beyng moued with pitie more than with zeale and trueth: ſayd he would refuſe none immediatly vpon their repentaunce. <hi>Meletius</hi> moued with trueth &amp; zeale, affirmed that he would receiue none, except they ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the fruites of true repentaunce, by long triall and proofe of ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſayth farther: <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tigit Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum martyrium ſubire, &amp; deceſſit bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ille:</hi> It fell out that Peter ſuffered Martyrdome and died a bleſſed man: and they that held with Peter were called the Catholicke Church: they that dyd ſticke to <hi>Meletius</hi> were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Churche of Martyrs: very few ſtode with Peter: the moſt of the priſoners ſtode with <hi>Meletius,</hi> who called his Church the Church of Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyrs: which were ſuch as would take vp Chriſtes Croſſe and folow him. The Church of Rome beyng moued neither with pitie, zeale, truth, reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor honeſty, but onely with ambition
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12269:58"/> and couetouſneſſe refuſeth none, ſo they will ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be of that Catholicke Church. Traytours, mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therers, théeues, coſeners, cutters, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulters, baudes, ſtrumpets and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graceleſſe perſons may vpon the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſafe acceſſe to Rome and be of that Church.</p>
            <p>Whereas theſe men alledge Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of place, and perſons, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng hable to proue Succeſſion of true doctrine: we may ſay their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is nothyng worth. For that is not a iuſt Succeſſion, which lacketh the puritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtolicke doctrine, &amp; right vſe of the Sacramentes. Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of doctrine is the true and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible marke of the true Church. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap:</hi> 44.</note> ſayth: they are not alwayes true Miniſters, which ſéeme ſo to be: but they which kéepe the doctrine of the Apoſtles. S. Paule ſayth: fayth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> commeth, (not by Succeſſion, but) by hearyng, and hearyng commeth (not of legacie, or inheritaunce from Byſhop to Byſhop, but) of the word of God. He ſayth alſo: be ye folowers <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:59"/> of me, as I am a folower of Chriſt. S. Ambroſe ſayth: <hi>Non habent haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. de Poenitent.</note> 
               <hi>Petri, qui fidem Petri non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent:</hi> They haue not Peters inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce that haue not the fayth of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Chriſoſt. ſayth: The pulpit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not a Miniſter, but a Miniſter the pulpit. Chriſt ſayd to the Iewes boaſtyng that they were the ſéede of Abraham: you are of your father the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.</note> deuill. They are not alwayes godly, that ſuccéede the godly. For S. Paul ſayth in the Actes: I know this, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 29.</note> after my departyng greeuous wolues ſhall enter in among you, not ſparing the flocke. Alſo of your owne ſelues ſhall men ariſe, ſpeakyng peruerſe thyngs, to draw away diſciples after them. He ſpake this at <hi>Miletum</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhops of Aſia. Chriſt ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by Suc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſion, deſolation ſhall ſit in the holy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> place, and Antichriſt ſhall preaſſe in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roome of Chriſt. Manaſſes ſuccée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Ezechias: Hieroboam ſuccéeded Dauid: &amp; at this day, by Succeſſion the Turke poſſeſſeth, and holdeth the foure Patriarchall ſeates or ſeas of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12269:59"/> the Church: Alexandria, Hieruſalem, Conſtantinople, and Antioche. <hi>Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Sariſ burienſis</hi> ſayth: <hi>In Romana Eccleſia ſedent Scribae &amp; Phariſaei:</hi> By Succeſſion, the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis ſit in the Church of Rome. Thus you ſée how Antiquitie, Vniuerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Succeſſion helpe the cauſe of the ſhakers of the ſhyp. It foloweth in the text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now when he had left ſpeaking he ſayd vnto Simon: launch out into the deepe, and let downe your nettes to make a draught.</hi> Chriſt hauing ended his heauenly Sermon, certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs of the truth of the ſame, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth himſelfe to be God, the Lord of heauen, earth, the ſea, and all that is in them. Hee ſayd vnto Simon, launch out into the déepe: Chriſt was able to geue fiſhe to Simon without launching out of his net, and without his labour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but his will was to haue him launch out his nette &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That which is ſayd to Peter is ſayd to al: <hi>Launch out into the deepe</hi> &amp;c. Euery man (of what eſtate, and
<pb facs="tcp:12269:60"/> condition ſoeuer he be) is commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded paynefully to follow his vocation with fayth. Man forthwith after his creation was ſet to labour: The Lord <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 15.</note> tooke man and ſet him in the pleaſant garden of Eden, to dreſſe it, and to kéepe it. It was ſayd to Adam after that he had taſted the forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fruite: <hi>In ſudore vultus tui veſceris pane:</hi> thou ſhalt eate thy bread with the ſweate <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> of thy face. The ſame is ſayd to euery man. Man is borne vnto trauaile (ſayth Iob) as the ſparkes flye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127. 2.</note> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou eateſt the labours of thy handes, thou ſhalt be bleſſed &amp; it ſhall be well with thée. Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſayth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kindome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is like to a man that is an houſholder, which went out earely in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to hier labourers into his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. This houſeſholder is God the father: The kingdome of heauen in in this place, is the preaching of the goſpell of Chriſt: The labourers are all men: The vineyard is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church. Why ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you heare all the day idle? goe ye alſo into the vineyard, apply
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12269:60"/> your vocation with fayth in Chriſt Ieſu. Laboure while you haue time, when the night commeth, no man can labour. Idlenes is the mother and nouriſher of all vices: which thinge hath bin obſerued in the Primitiue Church, where it was ordayned that euerye one ſhould liue of his owne labour. The which alſo the auntient Romanes kept ſtraightly, as writeth, Cicero in his booke of lawes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he affirmeth that in tyme paſt, no Roman durſt goe by the ſtreates, if he bare not a ſhew whereon he did lyue: to thend that it might be knowen, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he liued of his owne labour: and not by the ſweate of others. In conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof the Conſull did beare a battell axe before him: The prieſt a hat in manner of a Coyfe: The Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune a mace: The Cutler a ſword: The Smith a hammer: The Tayler a payre of ſheares: The Oratour a booke. All godly men heretofore haue laboured, and alſo haue continued in ſpirituall exerciſe. Noha planted a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 70. <hi>&amp;</hi> 88.</note> vineyard. The kinglye prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid
<pb facs="tcp:12269:61"/> laboured euen from his youth. The Apoſtle Paule ſuſtayned great <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> labours. Reade of that vertuous and painefull woman in the laſt chapter of prouerbes: ſhe eateth not her bread with Idlenes. A good leſſon for good huſwiues to remember: A good leſſon for ill huſwifes to follow. But what ſhall I ſay of the holye of all holyes? is it not written: <hi>Ieſus fatigatus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itinere?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 6.</note> Ieſus being weary of his ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney &amp;c? Such was his labour: he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed ſometyme among the Iewes: ſometyme among the Samaritanes: he trauailed to the ſea ſide: to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Read.</hi> 11. <hi>Ebru. of the fayth, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and reward of the godly.</hi>
               </note> to the wildernes: ſo much trauailed he, that his handes, féete, and whole bodye did ſweate droppes lyke bloud trickeling downe to the ground: and all for the redemption of miſerable man: to deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of the deuill. It is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the praiſe of Cyrus king of Perſia, that in tyme vacant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the affaires of his realme, he with his owne handes, had plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted innumerable trées, which long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he dyed brought forth abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12269:61"/> of fruite. And for the cunnyng and delectable order in ſetting of them, it was exceeding maruelous to all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beheld the princes induſtrye. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus that famous king of Arago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, being miſlyked of one <hi>Matthaeus Siculus,</hi> a man of great holines, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he laboured with his owne handes: aunſwered ſmilingly: <hi>Nunquid Deus &amp; natura nequidquam Regibus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dederunt?</hi> Hath God and nature geuen handes to kinges for naught?</p>
            <p>All creatures laboure: the Angels labour: they are ſayd to be the meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ebru.</hi> 1.</note> of God, and miniſtering ſpirites. The ſunne laboureth continually: The ſtarres are doing: The moone neuer ſtaieth: The fier can not be without making ſome worke: The ayre is neuer idle, but is doing after his manner: The earth is neuer at reſt: ſhe bringeth fourth naturally her plantes &amp; other fruites: The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, floudes, fountaynes frauaile co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. Theſe litle creatures: Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Bees, Emets, Conies, doe pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully labour. And ſhall man be idle?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:62"/>
            <p> Tyme in this matter muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. make haſt in youth. <hi>Aeſtas non ſemper fuerit componite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dos:</hi> While the ſunne ſhineth make haye: The tyde muſt be taken when it commeth. Make haſt in youth, that in olde age you may reioyce, In death haue good report, and after burial liue for euer. But many geue themſelues to ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitye, and neuer leaue it, till they be come to themſelues a moſt miſerable miſerye: to their frendes a ſhame and ſorrow: to their enimies a ioy: to the common weale a burthen: and to the common people a ieſting ſtocke. The tyme of youth (eſpeciallye here) is to be obſerued. In youth Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der banquiſhed India: Scipio Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus the Weſt and South: Pompee ſurnamed the great, Spayne: Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Germany: Achilles Troy.</p>
            <p>Idlenes is a mother of trifles, a ſtepdame of vertu, an image of death, a nurſe of al euill, a pillow of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ground of all miſchiefe, a contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous peſtilence, a ſinke of ſinne, and a foule puddle of all vices. <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. Pedago lib.</hi> 2.</note>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12269:62"/> ſayth: <hi>vita olioſa, non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta appellanda:</hi> An idle lyfe is not to be called a lyfe. Seneca complayneth that we loſe a great part of our tyme in doing nothing: a greater part in doing euill: and the greateſt part of all doing thinges which nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne vs. Idlenes bringeth forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes: idlenes corrupteth the minde, and cauſeth infamie. <hi>Quaeritur Aegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthus quare ſit factus adulter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In promptu cauſa eſt, deſidioſus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat:</hi> If it be demaunded why <hi>Egiſthus</hi> became an adulterer: the matter is ſone aunſwered, forſoth he was idle. Idlenes bringeth beggary, Prouerb: 10. 20. 23. 28. From idlenes are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as moderate labour preſerueth health (as phiſitians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port:) ſo Idlenes weakeneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, diminiſheth ſtrength, and bringeth many infirmities by ill digeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce commeth loſſe of tyme: the day loſt, the night commeth: the night when no man can worke. The day is but ſhort, our lyfe is ſoone gone. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while we haue tyme let vs doe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 6. 10.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:63"/> good to all men: eſpetially to them which are of the houſhold of fayth.</p>
            <p>Hence commeth all miſchiefe: While men ſlept the enemie came &amp; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.</note> ſowed tares among the wheate, and went his way: When men runne not forward in the race of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: when men ſeeke not to knowe Chriſt Ieſus crucified: when men haue vertue in deteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: behold, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than our auncient enemie beſtyrreth himſelfe, and ſoweth the tares, and darnell, of hereſies, ſeditions, vice, and vilanye in the hart of man. The <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ. Hexame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.</note> Crabbe ſayth S. Ambroſe delighteth very much to eate Oyſters: But for that the Oyſters are ſo ſtrongly fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with two hard ſhelles which he can not breake by ſtrength: he wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth diligently to bring the Oyſters out of the water into the ſunne, and by helpe of the ayre and winde the Crabbe preſenly putteth a litle ſtone into the Oyſter as he gapeth: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he can not cloſe or bring together agayne his ſhelles. Than afterward the Crabbe without daunger putteth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12269:63"/> in his clawes and eateth the meate of the Oyſter at his pleaſuure.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo ſayth he: when men are geuen to idlenes, &amp; open their mindes vnto ſenſuall pleaſures: the deuill commeth &amp; caſteth into their mindes and hartes euill cogitations in ſuch ſort that their ſhell which before did defend them: can not be drawen cloſe together agayne: and than eaſely doth he vtterly deuour them. Idlenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of men wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſtes, and of beaſtes monſters. We ſhall finde the cauſes of all miſchiefe in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, to ſpring of idle perſons: they are the firebrandes of ſedition: and the cauſes of all ciuill diſſention. King Dauid whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.</note> himſelfe to idlenes, and ſlacked to launch his net into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> déepe: commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted two horrible ſinnes: adultery, and murther. As long as Sampſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fought <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudic.</hi> 16.</note> with the Philiſtines, he could not be taken of his enemies, but after that he ſlept in the boſome of a woman, and idlely continued with her: by and by he was taken and made blinde by
<pb facs="tcp:12269:64"/> his enemies. Kyng Salomon, after <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.</note> he gaue him ſelfe to eaſe, was ſeduced and beguiled of women: but when he was exerciſed in building the temple, he was in the ſtate of grace. Watch ye therefore good Chriſtians. For I know you are not holyer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dauid, ſtronger then Samſon, nor wiſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Salomon.</p>
            <p>Idle perſons haue bene plagued &amp; ſhalbe plagued. Terrible is that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Take from him that péece and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 19. 14. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> giue it to him that hath x. péeces. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was deſtroyed with brimſtone &amp; fire, for pride, fulnes of meat, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of idlenes and vnmercyfulnes. S. Paule writyng to Theſſ. ſayth we <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ. cap.</hi> 3. 11.</note> haue heard that there are ſome which walke among you inordinatly, and worke not at all. &amp;c. If there be any that wil not worke: let him not eate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amâſis</hi> a noble kyng of Egypt made a law, that yearely euery man ſhould make a recknyng to the rulers of his Prouinces, or countreis, how and by what occupation he liued: and he that either would not do this: or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12269:64"/> ſhew by what lawfull meanes he got his liuyng, ſhould dye. The ſame law <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aulus Gel. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 7</note> had the Areopagites. The ſame law Solon borowed from the Egyptians, &amp; made for the Athenians. I would the ſame law were made in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. It was prouided by the law of Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, that he that was found an idle per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon ſhould loſe his head. The Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſophiſtes wiſe men of India, had idlenes in ſo great deteſtation, that when meat was ſet on their tables, they vſed to demaund of their young men and mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s what they had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or done, ſince ſunne riſing: and if any were fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to haue bene idle, they loſt their dyner. Theſe wiſe men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted extremely all ſlouthfull perſons: And all ſuch (for that they had done no good in this lyfe) as though they had neuer liued, they buried among beaſtes. Notable was the cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the old Indians: for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was euery night before ſupper, to examine euery man how hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed that day: and if any could not proue that hee had bene about ſome
<pb facs="tcp:12269:65"/> good exerciſes, their vſe was to expell him out of their company. Whiche they did by the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Bées, which can abide no dranes, but as ſoone as any begynneth to be idle, they fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and kill him. But we ſuffer dranes in euery vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, moſt of all in the holy miniſtery. Then euery man muſt labour: Euery man muſt lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch. Whether? into the déepe: what to do? to make a draught: not to deceiue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to ſéeke temporall profite, but to edifie, to ſéeke the profit of the church, and glory of God.</p>
            <p>It foloweth in the text: <hi>and Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aunſwered and ſayd vnto him, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter we haue laboured all night, and haue taken nothyng: neuertheleſſe at thy commaundement I will caſt forth the net.</hi> We haue laboured all night, and haue not taken ſo much as one fiſhe. Note here the complaint of Peter, which is the complaint of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men and there with all note theſe wordes: <hi>at thy commaundement I will caſt forth the net:</hi> and laſt of all the ſucceſſe: <hi>that when they had this</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:12269:65"/> 
               <hi>done, they encloſed a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of fiſhes. &amp;c.</hi> we haue fiſhed all night and haue taken nothyng. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fiſh in the night: ſuch fiſh without the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of God, without the preſence of God, without prayer, &amp; eſtéeme more their fiſhyng then the word of God: therfore their fiſhyng is vnlucky: many by inſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than are moued and ſtirred to euill artes: to theft, murther, vſurie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther horrible vices, theſe labour in the night. Many preach, no man amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: no man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of the denne of ſinne, into the light of faith. What is the cauſe? men labour in the night. Peter and his partners laboured all night, and tooke nothyng: Many with their partners labour all night, and take nothyng. What is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe? they labour in the night: They haue not yet receiued Chriſt into their ſhyp: they haue not the word of Chriſt to caſt forth the net. Doctour Luther no tabely ſayth: <hi>Quod paſſim premantur tanta miſeria homines, ſola increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas in cauſa eſt:</hi> Onely infidelitie or
<pb facs="tcp:12269:66"/> vnbelief is the cauſe that men are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with ſo great miſerie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement I will caſt forth the net.</hi> We learne here an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of faithfull obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in Peter, who was prompt, &amp; ready to obey the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of Chriſt, whom he knew not yet to be the ſonne of God. We know him to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God, yet we ſhew no ſuch faythfull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: how then ſhal we excuſe our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues? Simon declareth him ſelfe accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to his name. For Simon by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation is hearing or obeyng. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is an excellent vertue. Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is better then ſacrifice. Noah <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 15.</note> obeyed the word of the Lord, and he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 7.</note> was preſerued from the floud. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham obeyed the word of the Lord, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.</note> it was ſayd vnto him: in thy ſéede ſhal all the nations of the earth be bleſſed. Nahaman obeyed <hi>Eliſaeus,</hi> and was healed of his leproſie. Incomparable <note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.</note> was the obedience of Chriſt. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> obey God: ſubiectes obey your Prince: Children obey your parents: ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes obey your maiſters: wiues
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12269:66"/> obey your huſbandes. Simon did caſt forth the net, but how? at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt. This is a profitable doctrine. Whatſoeuer ye doe in word <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collo.</hi> 3. 17</note> or déede, doe all in the name of the Lord Ieſus, giuyng thankes, to the Father by him. Euery man ought to launch out his net in the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: The Prince, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Preacher, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrat, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Houſholder, the Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Plowma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. For Chriſt ſaith w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out me ye can doe nothyng. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord build the houſe, their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is but loſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> build it. Except the Lord kéepe the Citie, the watchman waketh but in vaine. Read the whole Pſalme. By the onely frée goodneſſe &amp; gift of God, is the houſe and houſhold mainteined: the Citie defended: meat miniſtred: children obtained. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word of Chriſt, in runnyng it helpeth not to be ſwift, in battaile it helpeth not to be ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, in féedyng the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſi.</hi> 9.</note> flocke it helpeth not to be wiſe, to Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches it helpeth not to be a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of much vnderſtandyng, to be had in fauour it helpeth not to be cunnyng. Without the word of Chriſt, my fiſhyng, my
<pb facs="tcp:12269:67"/> plantyng, my wateryng, and all my labour is nothyng worth. Gregory ſayth well: <hi>Niſi intus ſit qui doceat, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſum lingua docentis laborat:</hi> Except he be within that teacheth, the toung of the teacher laboureth in vaine. Xer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes that great kyng of Perſia, which inuaded Grece with ſeuen hundreth thouſand of his owne people, and iij. hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſand ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſouldiours: was vanquiſhed by a fewe Greekes. Why? he launched not, he inuaded not in the name of Chriſt. The Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.</note> in the name of God paſſed ſafely through the red ſea. At the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iehoſ.</hi> 6.</note> of God they compaſſed Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho ſeuen tymes, and all thynges fell out vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt proſperouſly. Sam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudic.</hi> 15.</note> in the name of God, made heapes of his deadly enemies, with the iawe of an Aſſe: with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iawe of an Aſſe he ſlew a thouſand men. Dauid ſayd to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.</note> proude Goliath, who defied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hoſt of Iſraell: Thou commeſt to me with a ſword, a ſpeare, and a ſhield: but I come to thée in the name of the Lord of hoſtes, the God of the hoſt of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12269:67"/> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt railed on. By this name and omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t word (as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome noteth) the ſtone was direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.</note> to the forehead of Goliath, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it did ſinke, and he fell groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng to the earth. And ſo the armed was ſlayne by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnarmed: the Giant, by a Dwarf: and the ſkilfull in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial affaires, by one that could no ſkil but of kéepyng ſhéepe. The cauſe was, for that he had his helpe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, through the truſt whereof he ſtrake the blaſphemer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> into the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. In the ſame name, oftentymes a poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> groweth to great wealth, and in fauour with God and man.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer therefore purpoſeth to haue good ſucceſſe in his affaires, muſt of neceſſitie launche out with Simon into the déepe, and that in the name of Chriſt: he muſt become Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a hearer, and a Diſciple: Of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie he muſt heare, read, learne, &amp; meditate the word of God, according to the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: firſt ſéeke the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6,</note> kyngdome of God and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp;c. He muſt receiue Chriſt into
<pb facs="tcp:12269:68"/> his ſhyp: that is, moſt faythfully and humblely pray him to bleſſe his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. That is the way to thriue in this world and in the world to come. There are many launchers, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now a dayes, which launch out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the déepe, not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſt, but in the name of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they make draughtes, deuiliſh draughtes, by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, by periuries, by coſenyng, by lying, theft, murther, flattering, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, and ſuch like vilanie. Is this the way to thriue?</p>
            <p>Many obiect why the indeuours of godly men often tymes haue ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and the indeuours of the wicked haue good ſucceſſe. God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this ordinaunce, that all thynges to the godly ſhould proſper and come to good effect, and to the euill ſhould decay &amp; come to euill effect. But Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than troubleth this ordinaunce, as it is ſayd: The Serpent ſhall byte his héele: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is Sathan ſhall afflict Chriſt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> &amp; his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers with all maner of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries incident to man: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng God vſeth a pollicie againſt Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12269:68"/> maketh that which ſéemeth a curſe, a bleſſing: &amp; that which ſéemeth a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to be a curſe. Ioſeph obeyed his fathers commaundement, and went vnto his brethren, and his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the inſtinct &amp; motion of Sathan, ſold him: but God turned this into bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. So we read of Dauid, ſo of the Apoſtles, &amp; of many other, whoſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes haue bene turned into bleſſinges.</p>
            <p>This is the condition and ſtate of men in this world. Generally good men lyue in aduerſitie, and wicked men in proſperitie. I ſay generally. For it commeth ſometymes to paſſe, that good men lyue in proſperitie and wicked men in aduerſitie. But this ſeldome falleth out, and among a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred good men, ſcarſe one or two lyue proſperouſly in this world. The ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſentence therfore ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth firme and infallible: good men are plagued with aduerſitie: euill men floriſhe in proſperitie: accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prouerbe: <hi>Quo peior, eo fortunatior:</hi> the worſer man the better lucke. Chriſt playnly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.</note> ſheweth this condition and eſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:12269:69"/> mens affaires, in the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Diues and Lazarus. You ſée often tymes the moſt wicked me moſt fortunate, and the moſt godly moſt miſerable: But <hi>Reſpice finem:</hi> marke the end: and fret <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.</note> not thy ſelfe becauſe of the vngodly, neither be thou enuious agaynſt the euill doers. For they ſhalbe cut down like the graſſe, and be withered euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gréene herbe. Put thou thy truſt in the Lord, and be doyng good: dwell in the land; and verely thou ſhalt be fed. Delight thou in the Lord, and he will giue thée thy harts deſire. Lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch thou into the déepe, and let downe thy not in the name of the Lord, to make a draught, alwayes remembryng the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſaying of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet Dauid: Some put their truſt in chariots, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20. 7.</note> &amp; ſome in horſes: but we will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the name of the Lord our God. So much for this part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had this done they incloſed a great multitude of fiſhes, and their net brake.</hi> Here we learne the cauſe of proſperous ſuceeſſe, and bleſſing of the Lord which is: if at his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12269:69"/> commaundement we caſt downe our nettes. Here Chriſt by a wonderfull miracle proueth his Godhead. The circumſtaunces declare the miracle to be wonderfull: the labour of all the night loſt: the breaking of the net: the ſinkyng of the ſhyp: the callyng of partners out of the other ſhyp: the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomeng and great admiration of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and others, the ſudaine forſakyng of all their goodes, &amp; obedience ſhewed to the word of Chriſt. The like mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle we haue in Iohn. 21. The vſe of this wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull miracle is: that Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Meſſias, that lambe of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world: That Chriſt not onely is Lord of the land: but alſo of the ſea, and all that therein is. In an other place touching <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 27.</note> tribute: Chriſt ſent Peter to the ſea, ſaying: go thou to the ſea and caſt an hooke and take vp the fiſh that firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vp, and when thou haſt opened his mouth, thou ſhalt finde a péece of xx. pence: that take and giue it vnto them for me and thée. If Chriſt be Lord of the ſea, and all thynges ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in:
<pb facs="tcp:12269:70"/> thou whiche by fayth art made a member of Chriſt, haſt no cauſe to feare the ſurges, waues, and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the ſea, feare not: that which is ſubiect to Chriſt thy head, muſt of neceſſitie be ſubiect to his members.</p>
            <p>What ſignifieth the breaking of the net: who breake the nette: how the nette is broken: why the nette is broken: theſe thinges are to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Touching the firſt: The king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is lyke to a net, which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 47.</note> was caſt into the ſea and gathered of all kinde of fiſhes, which when it was full, the fiſhers drew to land, and ſate downe and gathered the good into veſſels, but caſt the bad away. So ſhal it be at the end of the world. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhall come forth and ſeuer the bad fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the iuſt, and ſhall caſt them into a furnace of fyre: there ſhall be wailing &amp; gnaſhing of téeth. The net is broken when the concord of fayth in the Church is broken, and men falle into wicked hereſies and errours.</p>
            <p>They breake the nette which fiſhe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12269:70"/> in the night, wanting the light of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſcripture, and blinded with the darcknes of errours, and ignoraunce. Euil men which breake the vnitie of of the Church, and fall into ſectes &amp; ſchiſmes, doe alſo breake the nette, which obey not, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God. Theſe are euill fiſhes which are not taken: or els breake the nette: that is: they fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth, and loſe the ſpirite of God. All that were conuerted ſtode not in the nette of fayth and vertue: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny went forth and mightely brake the nette, peruerting fayth, vertues, and Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Such fiſhes belong to the kitchen of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Arrius went forth: brake the nette, &amp; began a moſt peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſchiſme, becauſe he could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the Biſhoprick of Alexandria. Whoſe ſteps many doe follow. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued not in the nette, but went forth and brake the nette. So did Fotinus, Manicheus and other innumerable. Of ſuch S. Io. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. 19.</note> ſaying: they went out from vs, but they were not of vs. For if they
<pb facs="tcp:12269:71"/> had bin of vs, they would no doubt haue continued with vs, but that it might appeare that they are not all of vs. Of ſuch alſo ſpeaketh S. Paule. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1.</note> Now the ſpirite ſpeaketh euidently, that in the latter tymes ſome ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the fayth, geuing heede vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſpirites of errours and doctrines of deuils &amp;c. Falſe Apoſtles brake the net in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Primitiue Church as Luke writeth: Then roſe vp certayne of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 5.</note> the ſect of the Phariſies, which did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue ſaying, it was needeful to Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them, and to commaund to kéepe the law of Moyſes. To theſe breakers of the net, S. Paule ſayth: Chriſt is become but vayne to you: as many of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 5. 4.</note> you as are iuſtified by the law are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from grace. Of this companye were <hi>Himenaeus,</hi> Samoſatenus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander, and many other heretickes. Since the Primitiue Church, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſwarmes of heretickes haue broken this nette. Whereſoeuer God doth build his Temple: there by and by Sathan adioyneth his chappell. At this day becauſe the light of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12269:71"/> Goſpell ſhyneth clearely: legions of heretickes: (as Anabaptiſtes, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes, Libertines, Arrians, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtes, Romiſh Catholickes, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>milie of Loue, and others) breake the nette of the Goſpell. Wo be vnto the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12. 12.</note> inhabiters of the earth, and of the ſea. For the Deuill is come downe vnto you, which hath great wrath: becauſe he knoweth he hath but a ſhort tyme. Touchyng the Familie of Loue: I ſay this, the deuill tranſformeth him ſelfe into an Angell of light. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no great maruaile that this familie, beyng in déede a familie of Sathan ſhould tranſforme them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues into a familie of light: a familie of loue. God is light: God is loue. Chriſoſt ſayth: <hi>Haeretici omnia habent in ſimilitudine:</hi> Heretiques haue all thynges in reſemblance or likeneſſe. This familie is not a familie of true loue. It is a familie of blaſphemy: a familie of falſhode: a familie of pride: a familie of idolatrie: a familie of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce and follie: a familie of mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: &amp; to be ſhort a familie of all vice
<pb facs="tcp:12269:72"/> and vilanie. That this is true their fruites declare. The trée is knowne by the fruite. For proofe I refer you to the bookes, or rather bables of H. N. whom they name the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of GOD, where as he is a falſe and lying Prophet. I promiſed to proſecute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the Romiſh Catholickes are not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Church: as I haue already proued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhyp of Chriſt: ſo I infer they break the net of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell. I argue thus: they commit Idolatrye: Therefore they breake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> net. After y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the popiſh prieſt hath ſpoken theſe v. wordes: <hi>Hoc est enim corpus meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Which is one word more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer Chriſt left, and is of ſo great vertue (as they ſay) that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that word there can be no perfect conſecration: where as notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, Chriſt, his Apoſtles, the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, and the Gréekes, neuer vſed this word <hi>Enim.</hi> It is a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Papiſtes, moſt wickedly leauyng out theſe moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary wordes that Chriſt hymſelfe ſpake: namely, <hi>Which is betrayed</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:12269:72"/> 
               <hi>for you: Do this in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me.)</hi> After y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the prieſt I ſay hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former wordes: &amp; hath blaſted, breathed, and blowed, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bread: he knéeleth downe to it and worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it, ſaying in Latin: <hi>Agnus Dei qui tollis. &amp;c.</hi> O Lambe of God that takeſt away the ſinnes of the world haue mercy vpon vs. Thriſe doth he call the bread which he holdeth in his handes the lambe of God, which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the ſinnes of the world. This is abhominable Idolatry. The authour of this Idolatrous leuation or liftyng vp of the bread aboue the prieſts head, was Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the third, about the yeare of our Lord 1210. He commaunded that the hoſt ſhould be lifted vp aboue the prieſtes head at Maſſe, and that all the people ſhould fall downe and worſhip it. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſheweth him ſelfe. Here all men may ſée how auncient a thyng their holy ſackeryng is, which is cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the beſt and chiefeſt part of their Maſſe: whereas in déede it is the moſt wicked and abhominable part of the
<pb facs="tcp:12269:73"/> patched paltrye, of their maſkyng Maſſe. The lying Papiſtes therfore may be aſhamed to bragge that their deuiliſhe Maſſe came from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: ſeing that it is proued to be a new and late inuention of Antichriſt. The worde Maſſe is not in the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And (as hath bin ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) there was no tidinges of any Maſſe priuate in any doctour or Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell by the ſpace of ſix hundred yeares after Chriſt. Their oblation, they call <hi>Sacrificium nouum:</hi> A new ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Their Maſſe booke hath theſe wordes: <hi>Acceptum ſit omnipotenti Deo hoc ſacrificium nouu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> O that this new ſacrifice might be thankfully taken of almightye God. They may truely call it a new ſacrifice: for it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of before, that a wafer cake and a ſponeful of wine mingled with water, ſhould be an oblation and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the ſaluation of the liuing, and for the reſt and quietnes of all the faythfull that are dead.</p>
            <p>I know they will ſay they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not idolatre: for that which they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12269:73"/> hold vp is the verye naturall bodye of Chriſt, God and man. Therfore may they iuſtlye worſhip it. I aſke them how they proue it to be the verie body of Chriſt. They anſwere by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of theſe wordes: <hi>Hoc eſt enim cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus meum:</hi> a goodly profe. I reply, Chriſt ſpake theſe wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread as the holy ſcriptures, and all aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent writers doe witnes. It is agaynſt the veritye of a naturall bodye to be in moe places then one at once, as he muſt be in a hundred thouſand pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at once, if their doctrine be true. The article of our faith is that Chriſt is aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp into heauen and ſitteth on the right hand of God the father almighty, and from thence ſhall come &amp;c. Our ſauiour Chriſt tolde his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> oft a litle before his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he ſhould leaue the world and goe to his father. S. Marke ſayth: Chriſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.</note> was taken vp into heauen and ſitteth on the right hand of God. Wée reade in the Actes: This Ieſus which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1.</note> vp from you into heauen: ſhall ſo come as you haue ſéene him going
<pb facs="tcp:12269:74"/> vp into heauen. Of theſe wordes of the angells, we learne that as Chriſt went vp viſiblye, and was ſéene with the corporall eyes of his diſciples: ſo lykewiſe when he commeth agayne from thence, he ſhall come viſiblye, and be ſéene with the corporall eyes of all men. But neuer man ſawe him yet comming downe with his corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eyes: Therefore neuer came he downe corporall ſince his aſcention. S. Stephan ſawe him. Where? not in the popiſhe pixe, nor in their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.</note> bread, but in heauen. S. Paule <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.</note> heard him: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence? from heauen. S. Peter ſayth that heauen muſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.</note> holde Ieſus Chriſt, till the tyme that all thinges be reſtored, which god hath ſpoken by the mouth of all his holy prophets ſince the world began. This tyme is, till the daye of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If therefore they will haue Chriſt bodily at their Maſſes: they muſt tary till the day of iudgement.</p>
            <p>This doctrine that the ſacrament of the alter (as they terme it) is the true, naturall, reall, carnall, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12269:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſubſtantiall bodye of Chriſt, is a dreame of Antichriſt the Byſhop of Rome, and cannot be proued, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by holy ſcripture, nor by aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers. You haue heard the holye ſcripture clearely denyeth it. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo deny it. <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſayth: <hi>Duplex eſt autem ſanguis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum Alex. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>peda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go. cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>domini alter enim eſt carnalis, quo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempti ſumus ab interitu: alter vero ſpiritalis quo ſcilicet vncti ſumus: &amp; hoc eſt bibere Ieſu ſanguinem, eſſe participe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incorruptionis domini. verbi autem vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt spiritus, quemadmodum ſanguis carnis:</hi> The bloud of Chriſt truely is of two ſortes: the one carnall, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wée are redéemed from death, the other ſpirituall, wherewith we are annoynted. For to drinke the bloud of Ieſus is to be parttaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords immortality. The ſpirite is the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the worde, as bloud is of fleſhe. Theodoret an auncient father ſayth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret: dialog.</hi> 1.</note> thus: <hi>Chriſtus naturam panis non mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat:</hi> Chriſt chaungeth not the nature of the bread. Gelaſius ſayth: <hi>Non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinit eſſe ſubſtantia vel natura panis: &amp;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:75"/> 
               <hi>vini.</hi> It ceaſeth not to be the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce or nature of bread and wine. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen that old learned father ſayth: <hi>Si</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen. Hom.</hi> 7. <hi>in Leuit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſecundum literam ſequaris id quod di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt: Niſimanducaueritis carnem filij hominis non habebitis vitam in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis: litera illa occidit:</hi> If accordyng to the letter you vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that ſaying: Except ye eate the fleſhe of the ſonne of man and drinke his bloud, ye haue no lyfe in you: That letter killeth. It <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 53.</note> is the Spirit that giueth life: the fleſh profiteth nothyng. For ſhortneſſe of tyme, I muſt referre you to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of other auncient Fathers which make the caſe cleare. <hi>Tertul. contra Marcionem Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>August. Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra adimantum Manichaei Diſcipulum cap.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; Tom.</hi> 8. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 3. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 221. <hi>Cyp. de Coena Domini. Heſichi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in Leuit. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Ambroſ. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentis Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Chriſoſt. ad Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium Auguſt. in Ioh. Tract.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp; Tract.</hi> 26. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eraſ. in.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> of great learnyng &amp; iudgement ſayth thus: <hi>In ſynaxi Tranſubstantiationem ſero definiuit eccleſia:</hi> In the holy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12269:75"/> it was long and very late, before the church determined the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Tranſubſtantiation. Their owne breath bloweth agaynſt them: Doctour Tonſtall, ſayth: It was no <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tonſtallus de Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 65.</note> hereſie to deny their Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before their late Councell of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran. Doctour Fiſher ſometyme <note place="margin">Fiſherus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicam.</note> Byſhop of Rocheſter ſayth: The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry preſence of Chriſtes body &amp; bloud in the Maſſe, can not be proued by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Scripture.</p>
            <p>This deueliſh doctrine was neuer receiued in the Church, til Pope Leo: Pope Nicholas: Pope Innocent: Pope Honorius: and Pope Vrban Antichriſtian prelates thorow their tyranny brought it in, and compelled the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with fire and faggot (as the maner of the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nicall Papiſtes is) to receiue their abhominable doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. It is not much more then fiue hundred yeares, ſince their groſſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt to be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, &amp; was throughly receiued, and agréed vpon, about the yeare of our Lord 1215. in the Councell of
<pb facs="tcp:12269:76"/> Latera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was holden in Rome, where were gathered together a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ſwarme of Phariſaicall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, about the number of thirtene hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred pildpates, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which number eight hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred were mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, channo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; fryers, a broode of chicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes owne hatching. Laſt of all came pope Vrban the monke, in the yeare of our Lord a thouſand two hundred thrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and foure, and he made vp all the market: For he ordained a feaſt called <hi>Corpus Chriſti,</hi> in honour of the Sacrament: ſo that euer after that tyme the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was no more ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a ſigne, figure, and token of Chriſtes bodye: but for Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe God and man. And therefore was it reuerenced, worſhiped, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſenſed, and knéeled vnto, as they taught the people at their vnſacred ſakeringes.</p>
            <p>S. Auguſt. ſayth touching the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the olde law: Abraham, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Aaron, and other receiued the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Chriſt truely and effectually long tyme before that Chriſt either
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12269:76"/> had receiued fleſhe of the bleſſed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin or had ordained the Sacrament: and that euen the ſelfe ſame bodye that is receiued now of the faythfull. Of this matter S. Paule ſpeaketh: They did all eate of the ſame ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 3.</note> meate: And did all drinke of the ſame ſpirituall drinke: For they dranke of that ſpirituall rock that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them: and that rocke was Chriſt. S. Auguſt. alſo of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. de Symbolo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos. Tom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> children and other faythfull that neuer receiued the Sacrament wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus: <hi>nulli eſt aliquatenus ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum, tunc vnumquem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fideliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſauguiniſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> domini participem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri quando in Baptiſmate efficitur mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum Chriſti. &amp;c.</hi> No man may in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe doubt but that euery fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man is than made partaker of the body and bloud of Chriſt, whan in Baptiſme he is made a member of Chriſt: and that he is not without the felowſhip of that bread, and of that cup, although before he eate of that bread, &amp; drinke of that cup he hepart this world, being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnitye of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:12269:77"/> bodye for he is not made fruſtrate of the Communion and benefite of that Sacrament while he findeth that thing which is ſignified in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
            <p>The enemies of the croſſe of Chriſt mightfully obiect: Onleſſe ye eate the fleſhe of the ſonne of man and drinke his bloud ye ſhall haue no lyfe in you. I aunſwere if there be no other ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Chriſtes bodye whereby wée ſhall liue, but onely fleſhly eating with mouth, and teath: than what lyfe hath Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, Moſes, Aaron and other holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, &amp; Prophets that were before the comming of Chriſt: what lyfe haue a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of holy martyrs? what lyfe haue Chriſtian Children that being baptiſed in the bloud of Chriſt depart this lyfe before they can receiue the Sacrament? Shall we ſay they haue no lyfe? Or ſhall we condemne them of euerlaſting death? Or ſhall we thinke they ſhall neuer riſe agayne? And ſhall we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye Gods election? S. Auguſt. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12269:77"/> of our fathers ſayth: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſibile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Ioh. Tract.</hi> 26. <hi>Tom.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>(Manna) spiritualiter intellexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ſpiritualiter eſurierunt, spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter guſtauerunt:</hi> They vnderſtode Manna the viſible meate ſpiritually: they hungred it ſpiritually: they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted it ſpiritually.</p>
            <p>I aſke the defenders of tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, what body Chriſt gaue: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mortall or immortall. I reaſon thus: if he gaue his body: he gaue his mortall body, or his immortall body: But he gaue not his mortal body, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther his immortal body: Therfore he gaue not his body. I proue thus he gaue not his mortall body: <hi>accumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat menſae:</hi> for it ſate at the table. He gaue not his immortall body: <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dum reſurrexerat:</hi> for it was not yet riſen. Therfore he gaue not his body. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is a figuratiue ſpéech.</p>
            <p>I vrge their owne wordes agaynſt them. By and by after they haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that the bread is the body of Chriſt eſſentially, ſubſtantially and in déede: and the wyne his naturall bloud: they adde <hi>Sed inuiſibiliter &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effabiliter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aquinas</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:78"/> 
               <hi>&amp; non vt in loco non quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>queſt.</hi> 76. <hi>Lombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſenten.</hi> 4. <hi>diſtinc.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>aut quantitatiue:</hi> But inuiſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vnſpeakeablely, and not as in a place, not in qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie or in qualitie. Note I pray you, how fitly theſe thynges agrée: how the one is ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the other. For if the true, and naturall body of our Lord, which he tooke of the virgin Mary, dead, buried, riſen, &amp; aſcended into heauen (ſo they ſay) be preſent in the Sacrament: aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly that ſame body muſt haue quantitie and qualitie, &amp; muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a place: except that body was not naturall: or els now beyng in glory, hath put away all truth of a body. The Angels teſtifie of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied body of Chriſt: <hi>Surrexit no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt hic,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc.</hi> 16. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ecce locus vbi poſuerunt eum:</hi> He is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, he is not here behold the place where they had put him. Chriſt him ſelfe ſayth: behold my handes and my <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 24. 39.</note> féete, that it is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I my ſelfe: handle me and ſée, for a ſpirite hath not fleſh and bones as ye ſée me haue. If this body haue not place, qualitie, &amp; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie: it is not the ſubſtantiall, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12269:78"/> and true body of our Lord. Read S. Auguſt. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 57. <hi>ad Dardanum Tom.</hi> 2. Thus much concernyng the Lordes Supper.</p>
            <p>Alſo theſe men teach that we are not iuſtified by fayth onely. This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is falſe: Therefore they breake the net.</p>
            <p>They call vs <hi>Solifidia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:</hi> We may call them <hi>Nullifidians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I argue thus: the righteous man <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Habac.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> liueth, by his fayth: Therefore fayth iuſtifieth.</p>
            <p>Abraham was iuſtified by fayth: Therfore other are iuſtified by fayth. Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the father of all beleuers. The antecedent is proued: Abraham <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> beleued God and it was accompted to him for righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Abraham was iuſtified by fayth. 430. yeares before Moyſes gaue the law: Therefore fayth iuſtifieth &amp; not the law.</p>
            <p>That thyng onely iuſtifieth, by which the holy Ghoſt is geuen: The holy Ghoſt is geuen by fayth, and not by the law: Therfore fayth iuſtifieth
<pb facs="tcp:12269:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> and not the law. The firſt reaſon is proued by experience. The Galatia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s receiued the holy Ghoſt by preaching of the Goſpell: and ſo conſequently by fayth. The examples in the Actes of the Apoſtles, of Cornelius and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, and alſo the example of the Centurion proue the ſame. Fayth onely iuſtifieth Read. Rom. 1. 3. 4. and 9. chap.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sola fides:</hi> Onely fayth was very well knowen and vſed of auncient Fathers long a goe, and the vſe of the ſame hath bene in the Church ſince the tyme of the Apoſtles: By onely fayth, fréely, without workes: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the law. The tyme fléeth away &amp; therefore I will onely cote the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours and the places. Origen in his expoſition vpon the Romanes chap. 3. hath <hi>Sola fides,</hi> fayth onely. S. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of incomparable vertue and learnyng hath <hi>Sola fides,</hi> in his booke <hi>de Humilitate. <hi>Athanaſius</hi>
               </hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iij. chap. to the Romanes hath <hi>Sola fides.</hi> The eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t famous Doctour Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. vpon the Epheſians the ſecond
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12269:79"/> chapter <hi>Serm.</hi> 5. <hi>Sola fides.</hi> And in his Sermon of fayth and the law <hi>Sola fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi> S. Ambroſe vpon the iij. iiij. x. xi. chap. to the Romanes <hi>Sola fides.</hi> S. Hierome vpon the foure and v. to the Romanes <hi>Sola fides. Euſebius Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. <hi>Sola fides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude S. Auguſt. albeit not in expreſſe termes as the other, yet in effect hath it aſmuch: After diſcourſe of the merites of Chriſt: of fayth in Chriſt: and of the miſerable naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man: excellently he thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth: <hi>His igitur conſyderatis pertra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, pro viribus quas Dominus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſpiritu &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellinum.</hi> 13. <hi>cap. in fine.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dignatur: colligimus non iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri hominem praeceptis bonae vitae, ſed fide in Ieſu Chriſto: hoc eſt non lege operum, ſed lege fidei: non litera ſed ſpiritu: non factorum meritis, ſed gratuita gratia:</hi> Theſe thinges conſidered &amp; debated, accordyng to the abilitie whiche God hath graciouſly geuen me: I conclude that man is not iuſtified by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes &amp; rules of good life, but by faith in Chriſt Ieſus: That is not by the law of workes: but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of fayth:
<pb facs="tcp:12269:80"/> not by the letter, but by the ſpirite: not by merites and déedes, but by free and meere grace.</p>
            <p>The aduerſarie obiecteth thus: It is impietie or wickedneſſe to add any thyng to the holy Scripture: for that it is written <hi>Non addes aliquid neque minues:</hi> Thou ſhalt not add any thing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.</note> nor diminiſh: S. Paul ſayth, if an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 1.</note> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen preach any otherwiſe, let him be accurſed. And <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth good counſaile: <hi>De Deo est vten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum verbis Dei:</hi> When we ſpeake of God, we ought to vſe the wordes of God. <hi>Sola fide:</hi> By fayth onely is not to be read in holy ſcripture any where not in Paul him ſelf, out of whoſe 3. chap. of his Epiſtle to the Romanes it is alledged: Therfore to vſe exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely: <hi>Iustificamur ſola fide:</hi> We are iuſtified by fayth onely, is impietie, and Luther hath depraued, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted S. Paule.</p>
            <p>I aunſwere it is a falſe kind of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſettyng downe that thyng, for the cauſe whiche is not the cauſe in déede. Albeit the word <hi>Sola,</hi> written
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12269:80"/> with iiij. letters be not extant in S. Paule: yet notwithſtandyng wordes equiualent are there exta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, declaryng the ſame thyng, much more effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; plainly. As for example: <hi>Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur gratis:</hi> we are iuſtified fréely: <hi>Ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us gratia:</hi> by his grace: <hi>Abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> operibus:</hi> without workes: <hi>Dei donu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est:</hi> It is the gift of God: <hi>per fidem:</hi> By fayth. When S. Paule excludeth all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner workes: what els leaueth he but fayth alone?</p>
            <p>They teach &amp; maintaine Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Therfore they breake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> net. This word Purgatory is not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bible: but the purgation and remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes, is made by the abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God. Luc. 1. Mar. 2. Onely by Chriſt: So ſayth S. Iohn: The bloud <note place="margin">1. <hi>Io.</hi> 1.</note> of Ieſus Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs and maketh vs cleane fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all our ſinnes. So ſayth S. Mat. 1. &amp;. 26. Marc. 14. Luc. 22. Act. 13. Epheſ. 1. Hebr. 1. 9. 10. Apoc. 1. &amp;c. Swéete is that ſaying of S. Cyp. <hi>Sanguis tuus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cyp. de paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</note> 
               <hi>Domine non quaerit vltionem: ſanguis tuus lauat crimina: peccata condonat:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12269:81"/> Thy bloud O Lorde ſéeketh no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: thy bloud waſheth our ſinnes, &amp; pardonneth our treſpaſſes.</p>
            <p>The Eaſt Church of God whiche ſometyme was as great &amp; famous as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of the Weaſt, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they beleued in God &amp; his Chriſt &amp; knew there was both Hell &amp; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet of Purgatory they had no ſkil. In the late Councell begun at Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar by Pope Eugenius and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued and ended at Florence <hi>An.</hi> 1439. Purgatorye was concluded and not before in any auncient Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the enemies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe of Chriſt prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the ſame is of very great antiquity. Not much vnlyke are they to the olde <hi>Arcades,</hi> whoe ſayd in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of their Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye that they were a day or two elder then the Moone. It came from Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill and Plato and other Heathen writers. If a man aſke them where it is: Some of them ſay in Ireland: The Purgatory of Patrick: into the which (they ſay) they had once a key, and a valiant champion named noble
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12269:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> Nicholas, boldly and valiantly adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured in, and there did ſée wonders: Some of them ſay it is in Scicilie in the burning hill <hi>Aetna:</hi> And ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay: it is in the Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Thile, which is alſo called Iſeland. Syr Thomas Moore ſayd &amp; held for certaintie that in all Purgatory there is no water: no, not one drop: and that he would proue out of Zachar. 9. Doctour Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher ſometyme Byſhop of Rocheſter ſayd: There is in Purgatory great ſtore of water, &amp; that he would proue by the Prophet Dauid. Pſal. 65. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus</hi> ſayd: The Executioners and Miniſters of Purgatory be holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: Syr Thomas Moore ſaid: out of doubt they be no Angels but very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils. So ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſomely theſe dreames a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together. It ſerueth wel for their purſe &amp; purpoſe, and is the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable monſter that euer was whel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of the Babylonicall ſtrumpet.</p>
            <p>They maintaine frée will: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they breake the net. This word frée will is not in all the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but is inuented by proude men:
<pb facs="tcp:12269:82" rendition="simple:additions"/> which would ſet vp their owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and put downe the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt. The frée will of man is in fallyng, and not in riſing. Chriſt onely is free: we are <hi>Liberati gratia,</hi> but not <hi>Liberi natura:</hi> fréed by grace, but not frée by nature: and ſo likewiſe <hi>Iuſtificati gratia,</hi> iuſtified by grace, &amp; not iuſt by nature. S Paule <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galla.</hi> 5. 17.</note> ſayth the fleſh luſteth contrary to the ſpirite and the ſpirite contrary to the fleſh: theſe are contrary one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo that ye can not doe what ye would. Where is then frée will. We haue here ſtill a clogge. Conſider wel the ſeuenth chapter of the Epiſtle of S. Paule to the Romanes, from the fouretenth Verſe, to the ende of the chapter: and you ſhalbe able to ſtop the mouthes of all frée will men. His wordes are theſe: For we know that the law is ſpirituall: but I am car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſold vnder ſin. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche I doe, I allow not: for what I would, that doe I not: but what I hate, that doe I. If I doe now that whiche I would not, I conſent vnto the law
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12269:82"/> that it is good. Now then, it is not I that doe it: but ſinne that dwelleth in me. For I know, that in me (that is to ſay in my fleſhe) dwelleth no good thyng. For to will, is preſent with me: but I finde no meanes to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which is good. For the good that I would, doe I not: but the euill which I would not, that do I. And if I doe that I would not, then is it not I any longer that doth it, but ſinne that dwelleth in me. I finde then by the law, that when I would do good, euill is preſent with me. For I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite in the lawe of God, after the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man. But I ſée another law in my members, rebellyng agaynſt the law of my mynde, and ſubduyng me vnto the law of ſinne, which is in my members. O wretched man that I am: who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death? I thanke God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. So then, with the minde I my ſelfe ſerue the law of God: but with the fleſhe, the law of ſinne. We ſhall then be frée, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this mortalitie hath put on
<pb facs="tcp:12269:83"/> immortalitie: and this corruption hath put on incorruption.</p>
            <p>If any man will deſcribe the will of man not regenerate: he may note it thus: In naturall actions he may doe ſomewhat, but not without the generall grace of God: In morall &amp; ciuill actions lykewiſe he may doe ſomewhat, but not without the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all grace of God: In ſpirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, before he be borne agayne, and hath receiued light of the holy ſpirite, he can doe nothing at all. The tyme is ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, euen in the entrye of my third part. I will be ſhort. They inuocate creatures, <hi>Ergo:</hi> they breake the net. We muſt direct our prayers to God alone our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father in the name of Ieſus Chriſt. For it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum Deum tuum adorato, eum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>Math.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>colito:</hi> Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue. Albeit Chriſt is not here expreſly mentioned: notwithſtanding he is included: For the faythful pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, alwayes thinke vpon Chriſt. The publican prayed: God
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12269:83"/> be mercifull to me a ſinner. He <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 18.</note> thought vpon Chriſt. &amp;c. It is hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible (ſayth D. Luther) to thinke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon God without Chriſt: for that without Chriſt we haue no ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He is our onely mediatour vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: therefore no Saint is our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour. Chriſt ſayth: <hi>Ego ſum via,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>veritas, &amp; vita, nemo venit ad Patrem, niſi per me:</hi> I am the way, the truth, &amp; the lyfe, no man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to the father but by me. Which wordes S. Augu. noting ſayth: <hi>Ambulare vis? Ego</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Io. tract.</hi> 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 9. <hi>in cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſum via. Falli non vis? Ego ſum veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. Mori non vis? Ego ſum vita. Hoc dicit tibi Saluator tuus: Non eſt quò eas, niſi ad me: Non eſt quà eas, niſi per me:</hi> Wilt thou walke? I am the way. Wilt thou not be deceiued? I am the truth. Wilt thou not dye? I am the lyfe. This ſayth thy Sauiour vnto thée: there is no place whether thou mayeſt goe but to me: There is no way for thée to paſſe, but by me. No man knoweth the father but the ſon, and he to whome the ſon will reueale him. S. Paule ſayth: There is one
<pb facs="tcp:12269:84"/> God, and one mediatour betwene <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5.</note> God and man, the man Ieſus Chriſt. The kingly Prophet Dauid ſayth in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 15.</note> the perſon of God: Call vpon me in the day of trouble: ſo will I deliuer thée, and thou ſhalt glorifie me. The Prophet Eſay ſayth alſo in the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43. 25.</note> of God: I, euen I am he onely that for mine owne ſake doe away thyne offences, and forget thy ſinnes, ſo that I will neuer thinke vpon them. The ſcripture plentifully, and ſtrongly proueth this matter. What is more cleare, then the prayer which our Sauiour Chriſt hath taught vs? <hi>Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is horrible idolatrye to inuocate any creature, whether dead or aliue. They are not gods: for there is one onely God who is to be inuocated: Therefore creatures ought not to be inuocated.</p>
            <p>Creatures are not omnipotent, neither knowe they the hartes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: here is none excepted neither Mary, nor Peter, nor any creature eſle: Therfore they ought not to be inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, or prayed vnto.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:12269:84"/>
            <p> Prayer muſt be made with fayth:</p>
            <p>But fayth onely muſt be repoſed in God:</p>
            <p>Therfore onely God is to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto.</p>
            <p>We haue no expreſſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or example in holy ſcriptures concerning inuocation of creatures: Therefore it cannot be done with fayth and good conſcience. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe doth expreſlye prohibite it, and the prophets condemne it. It is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt marke and playne note of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. To beleue in other creatures beſide Chriſt, is not to beleue in Chriſt:</p>
            <p>But the Papiſtes beleue in other creatures beſide Chriſt: <hi>Ergo</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue not in Chriſt. The argument is ſure, and the concluſion muſt néedes folow. I ſpeake of a true and a right beliefe. Theſe thinges Paule neuer planted: Apollo neuer watered: Chriſt neuer encreaſed. If holy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine. were now aliue, &amp; heard ſuch wicked and blaſpemous opinions: he would ſurely ſay vnto theſe men as
<pb facs="tcp:12269:85"/> he once ſayd to Iulianus: a Pelagian heretique with his ſect: <hi>Mira dicitis:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iulian. Pelag. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Tom.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>noua dicitis: falſa dicitis. Mira ſtupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: noua cauemus: falſa conuincimus:</hi> Marueilous thinges you ſpeake, new thinges you ſpeake, falſe thinges you ſpeake. Your marueilous thinges wée are aſtonied at, your new ſayings wée will beware of, your falſe ſayings wée will conuince. The more you ſtirre, the faſter you ſtick: the longer ye ſtriue the weaker ye are: you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not blind the Sunne beames: will ye nil ye the truth will conquere. There is no wiſedome, there is no policie, there is no cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaile againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>The truth of God will ſtand: va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitye will fall of it ſelfe. Remember <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</note> the counſaile of Gamaliel: fight not agaynſt the ſpirite of God.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſée how the nette is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by corrupt doctrine: The ſame is alſo broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ill maners. Of the firſt you haue ſomewhat heard: Now a word touching the ſecond. The ſame breakers of the nette: the ſhakers of the ſhip ſtill breake the nette with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12269:85"/> their ill manners. They ſhew intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in refuſing to come to the Church: Some of them main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne trayterous perſons beyond the ſea: and on this ſide the ſea: and of theſe, ſome they make their Bailifes, ſome their ſtewardes: ſome their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: ſome their Scholemaiſters: and ſome their ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of chiefe truſt to waite vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my Lady. This I know. Some they ſuborne to vtter their dregges, by writinges and other lewd practiſes. They are not content to be euill themſelues, but they inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour alſo as much as in them lyeth to make other partakers of their euill. If you make dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſearch: you ſhall finde fat bulles of Baſan of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in Cathedrall Churches: du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me dogges, and hinderers, as farre as they dare of the Goſpell of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu. They are called <hi>Pastores a paſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do:</hi> Paſtors of féeding: and féede not at all: and <hi>Doctores a docendo:</hi> Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of teaching, and teach not at all: as alſo <hi>Mons a mouendo:</hi> a hill hath his name of moouing, and moueth not
<pb facs="tcp:12269:86"/> at all. Theſe truely are Caterpillers deuouring the ſwéete fruite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land. They ſhould be ſerued aright if they were rewarded with Caterpillers. All theſe men thinke that they can walke vneſpied, as though they had Gyges ring vpon their finger to goe inuiſible by. <hi>Non ſic (impij,) non ſic:</hi> not ſo (honeſt men,) not ſo.</p>
            <p>Now they are very bold: They are in their ruffe, and looke for a day: God I truſt will mercyfully kéepe vs from that day: And yet I can not ſée if they had their purpoſe, but they ſhoulde féele the ſmart of that day. They are weary of their welfare. The clemencie of our moſt clement Quéene Elizabeth, hath long tyme bin abuſed: Now it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iuſtice to bridle inſolencie. The diſſeaſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of lawes which now attacheth ſo many, can by no meanes be cured but by the medicine of correction. For all this we are not to iudge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne theſe men to the pit of Hell. Leaue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and condemnation
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12269:86"/> to God. The right hand of God is mightful: he is able of ſtones: of hard &amp; Idolatrous hearts to rayſe vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to Abraham: He is able to turne the great Turke, &amp; the Cane of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thai. Lord if it be thy will enlighten their dimme eyes with the influence of thy heauenly grace, that they may ſée the truth: open their vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eares, that they may heare the truth: mollifie their hard hearts, that they may loue and embrace the truth: that thou mayeſt be glorified: thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple edified: and Sathan confounded. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A queſtion is propoſed: Why is the net broken? I aunſwere: <hi>Oportet haereſes eſſe:</hi> There muſt be alſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they whiche are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you might be knowen. Many are called, fewe are choſen. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 20.</note> This place aunſwereth an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of aduerſaries agaynſt the true Church.</p>
            <p>In the true Church are no ſectes:</p>
            <p>But in your Church are ſectes:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> your Church is not the true Church.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12269:87"/>
            <p> I aunſwere: <hi>Oportet haereſes eſſe:</hi> There muſt be hereſies &amp;c. Alſo they went from vs but they be not of vs. Furthermore tares are amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wheat. Secondly I ſay this Argument is nought. Heretiques are among the elect: Sathan among the children of God. Goates among ſhéepe. Tares among wheat: ill fiſhes among good: thornes among lilies: falſe brethren, falſe Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: veſſels of diſhonour, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g veſſels of honour. <hi>Ergo,</hi> heretiques are no here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques: Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Goates are no goates: tares are no tares: and ſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt. What wiſe kynde of reaſonyng is this? Are not hypocrites in the Church you know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which was amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the gheſtes at the mariage of the kynges ſonne: without a wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: The mariage was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with gheſtes good and bad.</p>
            <p>Take a Foxe, tye him vp with a chayne and cheriſh him with bread &amp; milke and howſoeuer you can whole vij. yeares, &amp; if the chayne breake the Foxe will get away &amp; runne into the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12269:87"/> wood. A Foxe wilbe a Foxe. Many falſe Chriſtians, two legged Foxes now tyed with the chayne of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and fed with the ſwéeteneſſe of the land, outwardly ſhewe them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues conformable to lawes, loyall and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſubiectes. Such Prince ſuch ſubiectes commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly for the tyme: But if the chayne of gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and life of Quéene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (whoſe life God long continue) ſhould breake: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly theſe Foxes: theſe hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes would runne to Rome.</p>
            <p>He that doth euill, let him do euill <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22. 11</note> ſtill: He which is filthy let him be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtill: and he that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill: and he that is holy, let him be holy ſtill.</p>
            <p>Albeit Goates féede with Shéepe: they ſhall not ſtand on the right hand with Shéepe. Albeit chaffe is threſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with wheat, it ſhall not be caried into the barne with wheat. Albeit ill fiſhes ſwimme with good fiſhes with in the net of our Lord: they ſhall not be put into veſſelles with good fiſhes but caſt away. Let no man forſake
<pb facs="tcp:12269:88"/> the wheat of Chriſt for darnell ſake: neither the flooer of Chriſt for chaffe ſake: neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great houſe of Chriſt for veſſelles of diſhonour: neither the net of Chriſt for ill fiſhes: neither the lillyes for thornes: neither true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians for hipocrites: neither the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God for Sathans ſake.</p>
            <p>Preaſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt with this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people to heare the ſwéet, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable word of God. Beleue it, loue it, doe it. Know the true Church: be of the true Church: continue in the true Churche: depart not with the Rauen out of the Arke. With Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the name of Chriſt, launche out into the déepe, to make a draught: Euery man folow his vocation with inuocation: with prayer. So ſhall yée haue proſperous ſucceſſe with Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: ſo ſhall yée receiue the fruites of faythfull obedience: in this world peace, and quietnes of conſcience: in the world to come ſuch paſſing abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ioy: ſuch paſſing excellent bliſſe: as no eye can ſée, no eare can heare, no tongue can tell, nor hart can
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12269:88"/> thinke, purchaſed by Ieſus Chriſt for all thoſe which folow Simon in fayth full obedience: to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be all prayſe glory and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for euer and euer.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by Iohn Daye, dwellyng ouer Alderſgate, beneath S. Martines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1579.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Cum gratia &amp; Priuilegio, Regiae Maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
